<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Jus appellandi ad Regem Ipsum a cancellaria, or, A manifestation of the King's part and power to relieve his subjects against erroneous and unjust decrees in chancery collected out of the authorities of law / by Walter Williams ...</title>
            <author>Williams, Walter, of the Middle Temple.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1683</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 145 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 73 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A66455</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W2774</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R7919</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12529014</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12529014</idno>
            <idno type="VID">62733</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A66455)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 62733)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 952:14)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Jus appellandi ad Regem Ipsum a cancellaria, or, A manifestation of the King's part and power to relieve his subjects against erroneous and unjust decrees in chancery collected out of the authorities of law / by Walter Williams ...</title>
                  <author>Williams, Walter, of the Middle Temple.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 128 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1683.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
                  <note>Table of contents: p. [8]</note>
                  <note>Errata: p. [8]</note>
                  <note>With Wing W2776.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Law --  Great Britain --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Kings and rulers.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:62733:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:62733:1"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Jus Appellandi</hi> AD REGEM Ipſum A CANCELLARIA: OR, A Manifeſtation of the <hi>King</hi>'s Part and Power to Relieve His Subjects againſt <hi>Errone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous</hi> and <hi>Unjuſt Decrees</hi> in CHANCERY. <hi>Collected out of the Authorities of Law. By</hi> WALTER WILLIAMS <hi>of the</hi> Middle-Temple, <hi>Eſq;</hi>
            </p>
            <q>Rex Sapiens Judicabit Populum ſuum,
<bibl>
                  <hi>Bract. l. 3.107.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed in the Year MDCLXXXIII.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:62733:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:62733:2"/>
            <head>TO THE High and Mighty MONARCH, CHARLES II. By the Grace of GOD KING of <hi>Great-Britain,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Moſt Gracious Sovereign,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Aving ſpent many years in the ſtudy of your Majeſty's Laws, and conceaving that ſeveral for whom I was concern'd as Councel had been much wrong'd a while ſince by Decrees in <hi>Chancery,</hi> and finding that they were paſt hopes of being Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted There, I advis'd Petitions to be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred to Your Majeſty, <hi>the Fountain of Juſtice,</hi> thereby beſeeching Your Majeſty to relieve Your Petitioners, either by re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hearing the matter in Your Royal Perſon, or by referring it to ſuch fit perſons as Your Majeſty ſhould nominate: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon it was declared by ſome near Your Majeſty, <hi>That Your Majeſty could not le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gally grant your Petitioners Request; and that no Relief could be had againſt</hi> Chance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry-Decrees <hi>but by the Houſe of Lords aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembled in Parliament;</hi> which thing I ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended
<pb facs="tcp:62733:3"/>to be a great miſtake, and tended (as I conceiv'd) to the Outing of Your Majeſty of that Juſt and Neceſſary Juriſdiction, Preheminence, and Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty which is united and annexed to your Imperial Crown, and which to aſſiſt and defend to my Power I am bound by Oath: In diſcharge whereof I have made diligent ſearch for what evidence could be found in the Authorities of Law to make out Your Majeſties juſt Title to the premiſſes, and what I have found I have made a methodical Collection of, being, I hope, ſufficient for the purpoſe; whereunto I have alſo added ſome inſtances of the great miſchief it is to your Subjects, and may be to Your ſelf, your Crown and Dignity, that Your Majeſties Power in that matter is not put in practice. All which I humbly lay at Your Majeſties Feet, begging Your Majeſties acceptance and conſideration thereof, as it is the product of the unſeigned Fidelity and Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legiance of</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Dread SIR, </salute>
               <signed>Your Majeſties moſt Faithful and Obedient Subject, <hi>WA. WILLIAMS.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:62733:3"/>
            <head>To His Majeſties moſt Honourable PRIVY-COUNCIL.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Great Sirs,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <hi>NExt to His Sa-cred Majeſty, to
<note n="a" place="margin">
                     <hi>C.</hi> 4. <hi>Inſt.</hi> 53. <hi>Crompt. Juriſ.</hi> 35.</note> You all Honour and Reverence is due, as being Incorporate to His Perſon, and Whoſe
<note n="b" place="margin">C. 4. <hi>Inst.</hi> 54:</note> High Office it is, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the beſt of your Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments truly and juſtly to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſe and counſel the King in all things that may be to His Honour and Behoof, and for the good of His Subjects. And though His Majeſty is arm'd with ſeveral other Councels for ſeveral purpoſes, yet it is with</hi> You <hi>that he conſults and adviſes (amongſt other the moſt weighty Affairs of State)</hi> when, <hi>and</hi> upon what occaſion <hi>it is that He is to call to His</hi> other Councels <hi>for Advice and Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſistance. It appears by the</hi> Writs of Summons <hi>of the</hi> Lords <hi>to Parliament,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Cromp. Ju.</hi> fo. 1.</note> and by the Writs to the Sheriffs for Election of Knights and Burgeſſes, that it is by Your advice the King doth call His Parliament; for after the</hi> Salutem <hi>in thoſe</hi> Writs <hi>are theſe
<pb facs="tcp:62733:4"/>words,</hi> viz. Quia de Adviſamento &amp; Aſſenſu Concilii noſtri pro quibuſdam arduis &amp; urgentibus negotiis nos ſtatum &amp; defenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onem Regni noſtri <hi>Angliae,</hi> &amp; Eccleſiae <hi>Anglicanae</hi> concernentibus, quodam Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liamentum noſtrum, apud, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> teneri or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinavimus. <hi>If then it appertains to You to adviſe His Majeſty when it is proper to call His Parliament, it follows of conſequence that it appertains to You alſo to adviſe Him to call His other Councels upon occaſion: And</hi> hence <hi>I conceive it is that You have been Dignified in ancient Records by the name of</hi> Magnum Concilium Regis, <hi>and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by diſtingniſhed from</hi> Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num Concilium Regni,
<note place="margin">Co. 1 <hi>Inst.</hi> 110. cites Records to that purpoſe.</note> 
               <hi>which is the</hi> Parliament. <hi>Therefore, and in as much as frequent ſupplications have of late been made by divers to His Majeſty for Relief a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt miſtaken Decrees in</hi> Chancery <hi>with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eut effect, by reaſon of ſome Opinions that there was no legal Remedy in ſuch Caſes, but by</hi> Appeal <hi>to the Lords Houſe aſſembled in Parliament: I have, for the advancement of Juſtice, and maintenance of the King's Right of Juriſdiction, compil'd, and adven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tured humbly to recommend this enſuing Treatiſe to His Majeſty and Your conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; which if You vouchſafe to peruſe, I
<pb facs="tcp:62733:4"/>hope it will make it ſo clear</hi> that His Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty may lawfully relieve His Subjects againſt ſuch miſtaken Decrees in the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tervals of Parliament, <hi>as to confute all Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ponents, or at leastwiſe maniſeſt ſo much probability thereof, and that there is ſo much neceſſity for the uſe of it, as may induce You to adviſe and deſire His Majeſty to be further ſatisfied therein by the Opinion of His whole Colledge of Judges, who in caſe of doubt in matters of Law, our Law-Books ſay,</hi> are his particular and ſworn Councel;
<note place="margin">Co. 1 <hi>Inst.</hi> 110. <hi>vi.</hi> Jurament. Jn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticiarior. 18 <hi>E.</hi> 3.</note> 
               <hi>In doing whereof, I humbly conceive you will perform an act that will highly redound to the Honour of the King, &amp; welfare of His injur'd Subjects: my Zeal to</hi> Both <hi>which hath put me upon begging Your favourable Reception and Interpretation of this Labour of His, who ſubmits both</hi> Himſelf <hi>and</hi> It <hi>to Your Honours Command.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>W. W.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:62733:5"/>
            <head>The CONTENTS.</head>
            <list>
               <item>OF the mutual Obligation upon King and People in reference to Government. <hi>Sect.</hi> 1.</item>
               <item>What is Juriſdiction; to Whom it appertains; and How anciently exerciſed in this Kingdom. <hi>Sect.</hi> 2.</item>
               <item>What is meant by judging according to Equity, and by Whom it was anciently exerciſed. <hi>Sect.</hi> 3.</item>
               <item>Of the modern and preſent Power and Juriſdiction of the Court of Equity in Chancery <hi>Sec.</hi> 4.</item>
               <item>Of the Corruption and Miſtakes of ſome great Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellors, <hi>Sec.</hi> 5.</item>
               <item>That an Appeal to the King in the Intervals of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is an ancient legal remedy againſt miſtaken Decrees in Chancery, with the manner of procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding therein, <hi>Sec.</hi> 6.</item>
               <item>The inconveniencies that accrew for want of a conſtant relief againſt erroneous Decrees in Chan. <hi>Sec.</hi> 7.</item>
               <item>Whether the King ought, <hi>ex debito Juſticiae,</hi> to hear in perſon, or to grant referrences upon complaint to him made, againſt erroneous and unjuſt Decrees in Chancery. <hi>Sec:</hi> 8:</item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>PAg. 2. l. 19. for Statute 1 <hi>El.</hi> c. 10. r. <hi>Statutes</hi> 1 <hi>&amp;</hi> 5 <hi>El.</hi> c. 1. p. 19. in 2 marg. note, for 232, r. 233. p. 29. 2 marg. note, for 16, r. 66. p. 28. marg. note, for 33. read 13. pag. 33. in the 2 marg. note, fo. r. <hi>cap.</hi> p. 42. l. 24. for have, r. <hi>hath.</hi> pag: 48. marg. note, for 4, r. 3. p. 70. for <hi>Bracton</hi> r. <hi>Brit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton.</hi> ib. l. 13. for <hi>ſua</hi> r. <hi>ſuam.</hi> p. 71. l: 15: for 10: r: 20: p: 78: 2 marg: note, for 14, r 24: p: 9: l: 12: for 22d: r: 12th: p: 106: marg: note, for 32, r: 33: p: 119: in marg: note, for 37: r: 27:</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:62733:5"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Jus Appellandi</hi> AD REGEM Ipſum à Cancellaria.</head>
            <div n="1" type="section">
               <head>SECT. I. <hi>Of the mutual Obligation upon</hi> King <hi>and</hi> People, <hi>in reference to Government.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hoſoever will but con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider it, may eaſily diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern, that there is a mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual benefit accrues by <hi>Government,</hi> as well to the <hi>People</hi> as to the <hi>King;</hi> the end &amp; deſign of it being the protection of
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:62733:6"/>
                  <hi>Both</hi> from wrong and violence: And to the end this may be the better ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſh'd, both are mutually bound in <hi>England</hi> to act their part therein: The <hi>King</hi> is bound <hi>to govern by Law,</hi> and the <hi>People</hi> moſt of the conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable part of them are bound, and all of them are compellable to be bound <hi>to aſſiſt and defend all Juriſdictions, Priviledges, Preheminences and Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thorities, granted or belonging to the King, His Heirs and Succeſſors, or united or annex'd to the Imperial Crown of this Realm;</hi> the King by the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Conſtitution of his <hi>Kingly Office,</hi> and by his <hi>Coronation-Oath;</hi> and the <hi>People</hi> both by their <hi>Natural Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legiance,</hi> and by force of the Statute 1 <hi>Eliz.</hi> cap. 10. It is not a ſlight and mean tie that they are bound by, it is by a ſacred and ſolemn Oath, the greateſt obligation upon Earth, and the firmeſt bond of <hi>Humane Society;</hi> which whoſoever voluntarily breaks, either by a wilful <hi>acting againſt,</hi> or by a careleſs <hi>neglecting to perform,</hi>
                  <pb n="3" facs="tcp:62733:6"/>what he hath undertaken by it, I'll be bold to ſay, He is ſit Company for none on this ſide Hell, unleſs for ſome <hi>perjur'd Aldermen,</hi> or <hi>falſe Ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noramne-Jury-men.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Being thus engag'd, I think it highly concerns us all to diſcharge our Duty therein; and to that end it is neceſſary, in the firſt place, to underſtand what <hi>Juriſdictions, Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heminencies, Priviledges</hi> and <hi>Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rities</hi> do appertain to the <hi>King;</hi> for without That, the King cannot <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe</hi> His <hi>Juriſdiction,</hi> nor the People <hi>aſſiſt</hi> Him in it: And in as much as the <hi>King's Juriſdiction</hi> over His <hi>Court of Chancery</hi> is now doubted of by many, diſ-own'd by ſome, and by o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers thought not neceſſary to be put in execution; I therefore ſet my ſelf upon enquiry after the King's Part and Power in that particular, having had experience of the inconvenien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies the want of the uſe of it produ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="section">
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:62733:7"/>
               <head>SECT. II. What <hi>is</hi> Juriſdiction; <hi>to</hi> Whom <hi>it appertains; and</hi> How <hi>an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently exerciſed in this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>JURISDICTION, in the bare lite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral ſence and ſignification of the word, and <hi>ex vi termini,</hi> imports no more than <hi>Dire Droit,</hi> or <hi>Jus dice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re,</hi> a Power to pronounce, interpret or relate what is Law and Right, in any matter of Controverſie: But as neceſſary appendants thereunto, there are many Priviledges and Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thorities needful, to make up a full and plenary Power to adminiſter Juſtice, which are generally compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended within the meaning of <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſdiction;</hi> As, <hi>firſt,</hi> an Authority to <hi>Command</hi> the party or parties com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain'd againſt, before Him that hath Juriſdiction: <hi>Secondly,</hi> to <hi>Examine</hi>
                  <pb n="5" facs="tcp:62733:7"/>the truth of the complaint, and to <hi>hear</hi> the Defendants defence: <hi>Third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,</hi> to <hi>give Judgment</hi> according to what the Law is: <hi>Fourthly,</hi> to <hi>compel</hi> Obedience to, and Performance of that Judgment which is done either by Impriſonment of the perſon until he perform, or by ſeizing his Eſtate, or part of it, in ſatisfaction of the Judgment, which is the <hi>Coercive Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer</hi> of the Law, without which the reſt ſignifies but little.</p>
               <p>The right of <hi>Juriſdiction</hi> is a prize for which great Conteſts have been for many Ages in this Kingdom: the <hi>Pope</hi> for a long time ſtrugl'd with our Kings for <hi>Juriſdiction</hi> in <hi>Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>astical</hi> matters; ſome yielded to him, and ſome would not; The <hi>Houſe of Commons</hi> have often ſtrove with the <hi>Houſe of Lords</hi> for <hi>Juriſdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction;</hi> the King's <hi>Courts of Juſtice</hi> have often contended with one a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother for <hi>Juriſdiction;</hi> and now ſome would have it, that the King's own more immediate <hi>Court,</hi> his <hi>High-Court
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:62733:8"/>of Conſcience,</hi> would be ſo high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly unconſcionable, as to out Him from having any thing to do there.</p>
               <p>To find out the true Proprietors of <hi>Juriſdiction,</hi> for which there hath been ſo many pitch'd Battles fought, it is neceſſary to look a great way back, <hi>Origo rei inſpici debet,</hi> the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning muſt be conſider'd,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Deut.</hi> 32. 7.</note> 
                  <hi>Remember the days of old, conſider the years of many Generations; ask thy Father, and he will ſhew thee; thy Elders, and they will tell thee.</hi> After this manner will I make my Enquiry; for I know no <hi>Statute of Limitation</hi> in the caſe to bar the King by non-claim; but there is a Maxim in Law which imports the contrary, <hi>Quod nullum tempus occur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit Regi;</hi> and therefore what I find in old Authors as well as new, I will truly relate.</p>
               <p>By the Opinion of all an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient &amp; wiſe Politicians and Hiſtorians,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Bod.</hi> l. 4. cap. 6.</note> (ſays <hi>Bodin</hi>) <hi>Juſticiae fruendae cauſa Reges eſſe creatos;</hi>
                  <pb n="7" facs="tcp:62733:8"/>Kings were ordain'd for no other end, than for adminiſtration of Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, which is a full Authority that Juriſdiction appertained to <hi>Kings,</hi> even by their Conſtitution; and the ſame Author ſays, That ancient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the Kings of moſt Nations and Countreys were called <hi>Judges,</hi> and they thought no other Appellation or Title more honourable than That, and they delighted in nothing more then a perſonal, not only virtual, but actual, determining of their Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects Controverſies.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Moſes</hi> for a great while ſpent the greateſt part,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ex.</hi> 18.</note> or much of his time, ſometimes even from mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning until evening, in hearing and determining Controverſies between the people; But at length, finding that as the people encreaſed in num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, ſo did Suits, inſomuch that it was too hard a task for him to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patch all himſelf, he therefore choſe men of courage out of all <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and <hi>thoſe he made Heads over the people,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:62733:9"/>Rulers over Thouſands and over Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreds, over Fifties and over Tens, who judged the people at all ſeaſons: but the hard cauſes</hi> (matters of difficulty) <hi>they brought to</hi> Moſes <hi>himſelf to deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine;</hi> none of them pretending that becauſe <hi>Moſes</hi> had given them full power to judge the people within their ſeveral Provinces, that he had excluded himſelf from power of judging there, and examining whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther or no their Judgments were right and juſt.</p>
               <p>In imitation of <hi>Moſes,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Cook</hi> 1 Inſt. f. 168.</note> or af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the ſame manner, did the ancient Kings of <hi>England</hi> divide this Kingdom, firſt into <hi>Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties,</hi> and <hi>Counties</hi> into <hi>Hundreds, Hundreds</hi> into <hi>Manors,</hi> and <hi>Manors</hi> into <hi>Townſhips</hi> and <hi>Villages,</hi> and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed Juriſdictions in every Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion.</p>
               <p>In or about the time of <hi>H.</hi> 3. one <hi>Henry de Bracton,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Cow. Int.</hi> Title <hi>Bract.</hi>
                  </note> a learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Judge, finding that the Laws and Cuſtoms of the
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:62733:9"/>Realm, (which at that time were not reduc'd into writing) were often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times abus'd by unlearned men, <hi>Qui Cathedram judicandi aſcendunt ante<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam leges dedicerent,</hi> who became Judges before they had been Stu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents, and conſequently determined Cauſes rather after their own fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies than the Rules of Law: he there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore reſolv'd, <hi>ad vetera Judicia Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtorum perſcrutenda diligenter,</hi> to make diligent enquiry into the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Judgments and Reſolutions of juſt Judges, and to put the ſame in writing for the benefit of Poſterity, as himſelf ſays in the firſt page of his Book <hi>Of the Laws and Customs of</hi> England; and therein as to the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral ſtate of affairs, (the <hi>Pope</hi> ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving in thoſe days uſurp'd Juriſdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, not only upon our <hi>Kings,</hi> but upon many other Princes in Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual matters) <hi>Bracton</hi> ſays,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Bract.</hi> l. 1. fo. 5. cap. 8.</note> That under Emperours, Kings and Princes, are Dukes, Earls and Barons, great Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:62733:10"/>men of Renown, and Knights; there are alſo Freemen and Bondmen, and divers Authorities and Powers conſtituted under the King; <hi>Omnia quidem ſub eo, &amp; ipſe ſub nullo, niſi tantum ſub Deo, parem autem non ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bet in regno ſuo quia ſic amitteret prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptum, cum par in parem non habet Imperium; item nec multo fortius ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periorem nec potentiorem habere debet, quia ſic erit inferior ſuis ſubject is &amp; in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feriores pares eſſe non poſſunt potentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ribus ipſe autem Rex non debet eſſe ſub bomine ſed ſub Deo &amp; Lege, quia Lex facit Regem, attribuat igitur Rex Legi, quod Lex attribuat ei, videli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cet Dominationem &amp; Poteſtatem,</hi> And a little further, <hi>Et ſciendum quod ipſe Dominus Kex Ordinariam ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bet Juriſdictionem &amp; Dignitatem &amp; Poteſtatem, ſuper omnes qui in regno ſuo ſunt habet enim omnia Jura in manu ſua quae ad Coronam &amp; Laica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem pertinet potestatem &amp; materialem gladium qui pertinet ad regni Guber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naculum, habet etiam Juſtitiam &amp; Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicium
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:62733:10"/>quae ſunt Juriſdictiones ut ex Juriſdictione ſuae ſicut Dei Minister &amp; Vicarius tribuat unicui<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> quod ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um fuerit.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To the like effect he ſays in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther place, treating of Temporal Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſdiction, and Who it is that can and ought to judge, he ſays,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Bract.</hi> lib. 3. fo. 107.</note> That it is the <hi>King,</hi> and no other, ought to judge, if He alone could compaſs it, being thereunto obliged by tenor of his Oath; for at his Coronation he ought in the name of Jeſus Chriſt, upon Oath, to promiſe theſe Three things to his people that are ſubject to himſelf, 1. <hi>That he would command, and uſe his utmoſt endeavour, that per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect peace be continued to the Church of God, and all Chriſtian people, during all his time.</hi> Secondly, <hi>That he would earneſtly and ſtrictly forbid and inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dict all Pillaging, Extortion, Rave<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, and Wickedneſs whatſoever.</hi> Thirdly, <hi>That in all Judgments he would regard Equity and Mercy, that
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:62733:11"/>he might receive Mercy from God, und that all people by his Justice may en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy a firm and inviolable Peaee.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>He ſays further, that it is the Kings part and duty (he being Gods Vice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerent on Earth) to prefer right be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore wrong, Equity before iniquity, that all his Subjects might live ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly, that none of them hurt the other, and that every one of them may have and enjoy what to him of right belongs. He ought to exceed all his Subjects in Power; He ought to have no Equal, much more ought he not to have any Superiour, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially in adminiſtration of Juſtice, that it may be truly ſaid of him, <hi>Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus Dominus noster, &amp; magna virtus ejus,</hi> with a great deal more to the ſame effect.</p>
               <p>In the next chapter he proceeds, and ſays,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Bract.</hi> l. 3. ſo. 108.</note> 
                  <hi>Dictum eſt in proxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo de ordinaria Juriſdictione quae pertinet ad Regem,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>In the precedent Chapter the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitive and fundamental Juriſdiction
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:62733:11"/>which belongs to the King is treated of; it follows now to treat of the delegated, derived and ſubſtituted Juriſdiction, where a man hath no Authority of himſelf, but what is committed to him, as when he that doth ſo delegate or ſubſtitute ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, cannot himſelf determine every particular Cauſe, and to the end his labour may be the eaſier, by dividing the burthen amongſt divers other perſons, he ought to chooſe in his Kingdom wiſe men, fearing God, in whom there is ſincerity and truth of ſpeech, who hate Covetouſneſs, and of ſuch to conſtitute Judges, Sheriffs, and other Bailiffs and Miniſters, to whom may be referred as well Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtions upon doubtful matters, as Complaints upon injuries, who will not decline the courſe of Juſtice to the right hand nor to the left, for hope of Reward, nor fear of Puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. And a little further, treating of the ſeveral ſorts of Juſtices, he ſays thus; <hi>Item Juſticiariorum qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:62733:12"/>ſunt capitales generales perpetui &amp; majores a latere, Regis reſidentes, qui omnium aliorum corrigere tenentur injurias &amp; errores; ſunt etiam alii perpetui certo loco reſidentes ſicut in Banco, loquelas omnes de quibus ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bent warrantum terminantes qui om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes Juriſdictionem habere incipiunt praeſtito ſacramento; item ſunt alii Itenerantes de loco in locum ſicut de Comitat' in Comitat' quando<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> ad om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia placita quando<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> ad quaedam ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ali ficut ad Aſſiſas tantum &amp; Gaolas; Et qui authoritatem habere incipiant ſine ſacramento cum breve Domini Regis receperint de waranto ſunt etiam Justiciarii constituti ad quoſdam Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſas duas vel tres vel plures; qui qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem perpetui non ſunt quia expleto Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficio Juriſdictionem amittunt:</hi> That is to ſay, Of Judges ſome are chief, uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal, conſtant, and of greater power than others, always with the King, whoſe buſineſs it is to correct the Injuries and Errors of other Judges; and there are others that are of a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:62733:12"/>continuance, reſident in a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain place; as in the Bench, determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning all Pleas whereof they have a warrant to determine; all of whom begin to have Juriſdiction by taking the Oath of their Office. Alſo there are other Judges that move from place to place, as from County to County, ſometimes to determine all Pleas, ſometimes ſome particular Pleas, as Aſſizes only and Gaol-deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veries, whoſe Authority begins with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any Oath, when they receive the King's Writ for their Warrant; and there are Judges conſtituted to deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine ſome certain number of Aſſizes, as two, three, or more, who are not of conſtant continuance, but having done what they were appointed to do, they loſe their Juriſdiction. And a little further, <hi>Et quamvis quidem e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orum perpetui ſunt, ut videtur finitur ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men eorum Juriſdictio multis modis, ſcilicet mortuo eo qui delegavit, vel mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuo eo ſub cujus proprio nomine cauſa delegatur. Item cum delegans revoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verit
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:62733:13"/>Juriſdictionem, vel alium dederis Justiciarium:</hi> That is, Altho' ſome of the ſaid Juſtices are of conſtant continuance as it might ſeem, yet their Juriſdiction may be determin'd ſeveral ways; that is, by the death of him who gives them Authority, or by the death of him in whoſe name the Suit is begun, or when he that delegates, or gives the Authority, doth revoke the Authority and Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſdiction which he gave, or appoints another Judge. And to conclude that matter, he ſays, That no Judge ſo ſubſtituted or delegated by our Lord the King, can ſubſtitute or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legate another.</p>
               <p>Thus far <hi>Bracton;</hi> whence it is moſt clear, that all primitive and ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginal Juriſdiction was in the King, and all ſubſtituted and delegated Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſdiction was derived from Him on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and under ſuch limitations as he directed, ſo as the Judges did act juſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; the main charge of adminiſtring Juſtice being on Him; and he fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:62733:13"/>ſate himſelf in Judgment, aſſiſted by his <hi>Capitales Juſticiarios à latere ſuo reſidentes,</hi> who aſſiſted him in the exerciſe of his Juriſdiction, and eas'd him of trouble; but they ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver pretended to deprive him of his power of hearing and determining himſelf, or changing his Judges, or aſſigning them Juriſdiction as ſhould be needful, according to the modern Doctrine of ſome; for he had both complete Juriſdiction, and <hi>deſignati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onem Juſticiariorum,</hi> in himſelf; and it was upon good reaſon this power was originally placed by God in Kings, and conſented unto, and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved of by good men; for by the aſſiſtance of, and reaſoning with their Judges, they could never fail of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning right Judgment, and their affection to their Subjects (like a good Father to his Children) being equal to all, it is not likely they ſhould be partial in their Judgments; and their Royal Eſtate is ſuch, as not to value Bribes or Rewards:
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:62733:14"/>So that there is not ſo much reaſon to fear Injuſtice from a <hi>King,</hi> as from a <hi>profeſs'd Lawyer,</hi> (like my ſelf) whoſe aim and deſign (perhaps) from his Horn-book, was gain and profit, and to raiſe himſelf a Name and Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily in the world. I can but wonder then, whence ſtarted that humour in men, rather to truſt any body in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciding their Controverſies, than the King? ſure it could be from no juſt Principle.</p>
               <p>Beſides the fore-mentioned Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor <hi>Bracton,</hi> there are others of the ſame ſtanding, that maintain the ſame Doctrine.</p>
               <p>The next I ſhall name is one <hi>Horn,</hi> who about the time of <hi>Edw.</hi> 1. com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piled a Book <hi>Of the Laws and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of</hi> England, a great part whereof (as Sir <hi>Edward Cooke</hi> in his Preface to the 9th. part of his <hi>Reports</hi> affirms, were ſuch Laws as the Kingdom was govern'd by for about 1100 years then paſt; to which Book he gives a mighty credit, and in matters of
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:62733:14"/>difficulty is very frequently his <hi>ipſe dixit;</hi> and that Author ſays,
<note place="margin">Mirror 232.</note> That Juriſdiction is the chie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt Dignity that appertains to the King: and thereof, he ſays, there are two ſorts, and he calls them ordinary, and aſſign'd, which are the ſame with Original and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legated, as the other Author terms them.
<note place="margin">Ibid. 23.2.</note> 
                  <hi>Juriſdiction</hi> (Tays he) <hi>can be aſſign'd by none but by the King; and he may do it, becauſe be cannot without aſſiſtance perform ſuch a charge; and therefore it was of old ordained, that there ſhould be a Seat, and a Chancellor to keep it, and grant Writs remedial to all Complain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ants without delay.</hi> This was the Chancellors Province then.</p>
               <p>And again he ſays,
<note place="margin">Ibid. 234.</note> 
                  <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſdiction eſt un porat a dire Druit;</hi> a power of comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding right to be done; and this po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer God gave unto <hi>Moſes,</hi> and ſuch as hold the like place as he; and this power belongs unto the King within
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:62733:15"/>his Dominions, and He, by his Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority-Royal, makes his Juſtices in ſeveral degrees,
<note place="margin">Ibid. 235.</note> and doth limit to every one his po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer after ſeveral manners. And there he enumerates divers ſorts of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſions and Courts; and ſpeaking of the chiefeſt Juſtices of all, he ſays, <hi>They determin'd matters more or leſs, according to the nature of their Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion:</hi> From whence alſo it fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows, there were no Judges that had, or pretended to have, any Juriſdicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on originally or fundamentally in themſelves; but what all of them had, was by deputation and delega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion from the King. Furthermore, <hi>Edm.</hi> 1. out of his Princely care that his people ſhould be govern'd by certain and known Rules, cauſed the Laws and Rules of Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Britt.</hi> ſo. 1.</note> and diſpoſition of Property, which then to fore had been uſed in the Kingdom, to be put in writing, and publiſh'd in his own Name; and at the ſame time com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:62733:15"/>the uſe and practice of thoſe Laws in all points throughout his whole Dominion; ſaving, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways reſerved to himſelf, the power of repealing, altering, and amending of them, as ſhould ſeem good to him, with the aſſent of his Earls, Barons, and others of his Councel; and ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving ſuch Uſages and Cuſtoms as had been time out of mind uſed, ſo that they be not <hi>diſcourdants a droft.</hi> And there he proceeds in this man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, <hi>viz. <hi>En primes en droft de nous meſmes &amp; noſtre Courte avouns iſſint ordeyne,</hi>
                  </hi> &amp;c. which is to this effect, That firſt of all, in the right of Himſelf, and of his Court, becauſe he could not in his own Perſon hear and determine all the complaints of his people; and to the end that his charge ſhould be divided as is there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by appointed, he did ordain, and his will and pleaſure was, <hi>That his own Juriſdiction ſhould be ſuperiour to all the Juriſdictions in his Realm:</hi> So that in all manner of Felonies, Treſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſes,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:62733:16"/>Contracts, and in all manner of Actions real and perſonal, he had power to give, and cauſe to be given, ſuch Judgments as thereto belonged, without any other Proceſs, (where he knew the direct truth) as Judge. And there alſo he appoints, That the Steward of his Houſhold ſhould re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſent Him within the Verge, and he aſſigned him his Juriſdiction, which was, <hi>to hear and determine the preſentments of Articles which concern the Crown, whenſoever it ſhould ſeem good to the King;</hi> And moreover, he will'd, that Juſtices in <hi>Eyr</hi> ſhould be aſſign'd to hear and determine thoſe Articles in every County, and in every Franchiſe, from ſeven years to ſeven. And there he gives the like power to his Juſtices of <hi>Ireland</hi> and <hi>Cheſter;</hi> and wills further, That the Count or Earl of <hi>Norfolk,</hi> by himſelf or ſome other Knight, ſhould always attend upon the King and his Steward within the Verge of the King's Houſe, ſo long as he ſhould
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:62733:16"/>hold the Office of Marſhal. And there he appoints the Juriſdiction of the Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtices aſſign'd,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Britt.</hi> fo. 2.</note> 
                  <hi>to follow the King, and be where He was, if in</hi> England; <hi>and that they ſhould have conuſance to amend falſe Judgments, to determine Appeals, and other treſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſes done againſt the Kings Peace and Juriſdiction.</hi> He alſo appointed a Coroner to be in the Kings Houſe, and in every County <hi>(un Viſcount)</hi> a Sheriff; and that under thoſe She<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riffs there ſhould be Hundreders, Serjeants and Bailiffs, who ſhould attend upon the Sheriffs. He alſo ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed Coroners in every County, and allotted them their Juriſdiction. And moreover, his will and pleaſure was, <hi>That there ſhould be Juſtices al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways reſiding at</hi> Weſtminſter, <hi>or elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where, (where he ſhould appoint) to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termine ſuch common Pleas as the King ſhould command them by his Writs, ſo as the Pleadings ariſing thereupon ſhould be recorded.</hi> He ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tled the Juriſdiction of the <hi>Exche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quer
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:62733:17"/>Court,</hi> and ordained, That there ſhould be Juſtices aſſign'd for every County, to have conuſance in ſuch cauſes as the King ſhould command by his Letters-Patents touching Pety-Aſſizes, and of other things whereof the Kings will ſhould be they ſhould make record, and that there ſhould be Juſtices of Gaol-delivery in eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry County; And he granted to the ſaid Juſtices, that they ſhould have the keeping of the Records of the Pleas pleaded before them; But they were not to raſe or amend their Rolls, or to make Record contrary to their Enrollments; Alſo, that the power of the Juſtices ſhould be li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mited in ſuch manner, that they ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed not the points contained in the Writs or Preſentments of Jurors, nor complaints to them made, ſaving ſuch incident matter, as without which the original cauſes could not be determined. And he utterly for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bids and prohibits that any ſhall have power to amend any unjuſt or
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:62733:17"/>erroneous Judgment of his Juſtices, but only thoſe Juſtices which fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed Him and his Courts, (who thereunto were by him entitled) or Himſelf or his Councel; for that matter he ſpecially reſerv'd to his own Juriſdiction. He forbids alſo all his Coroners and Juſtices, except his <hi>Seneſchal,</hi> his Steward, and his Juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of <hi>Ireland</hi> and <hi>Chester,</hi> to make any Deputies to do any thing where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of they ought to make record, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the King's leave. He will'd alſo, That in Counties, Hundreds, and in the Courts of every frank Tene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, there ſhould be Courts held by the Suitors; and alſo in Cities, Towns, Boroughs, and Franchiſes, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Beſides this Book, written by King <hi>Ed.</hi> 1.'s command, and in his own name, a while after there was ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Book written, (by whom it is not known) called <hi>Fleta,</hi> and it was in the Reign of <hi>Ed.</hi> 2. or 3. And that Author ſays, <hi>That Judgment is
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:62733:18"/>a threefold act,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Fleta</hi> lib. 1. cap. 17. fol. 16.</note> of three per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons at the leaſt, the Judge, the Plaintiff and the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fendant, without which there can be no Judgment: Nor</hi> (ſays he) <hi>can any one Judge in temporal mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, but only the King, or his Subſtiutes and Delegates.</hi> And the ſame Author, in his Tract of the diverſity of Courts,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Fleta</hi> lib. 2. fol. 16.</note> ſays as followeth: <hi>The King hath a Court in his Councel, in his Parliaments when preſent, the Prelates, Earls, Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rons, Nobles, and other skilful men, who are to determine the doubts of Judges, and where, upon appearance of any new ſort of injuries, new remedies are provided; and where Justice is to be rendred to every one according to what belongs to him.</hi> He hath alſo his Court before his Steward in <hi>Aula ſua,</hi> in his Hall, <hi>who now</hi> (ſays he) <hi>ſupplies the place of the</hi> Capitalis Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtiar'; whereof mention is made in the common Writ of <hi>homine replegi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ando,</hi> who was wont to hear the
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:62733:18"/>Kings own Cauſes, to rectifie falſe Judgments, and to do Juſtice to Complainants, without Writ; whoſe Power, in part, the ſaid Steward of the Kings Houſhold hath. Alſo, the King hath his Court of <hi>Chancery</hi> in ſeveral places in his Houſe. He hath alſo a Court before his Auditors ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially appointed, to be near the King, whoſe Office extends but to the Juſtices and others of the Kings Miniſters,
<note place="margin">☞</note> to whom there was no power granted to determine what they heard, but to relate the matter to the King, that he might direct puniſhments according to the quality of the Offence. He hath alſo his Court and Juſtices, as well Knights as Clergy-men, (<hi>locum ſuum tenentes in</hi> Anglia) before whom, and not elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where, unleſs before Himſelf and his Council and ſpecial Auditors, falſe Judgments and Errors of Juſtices are reverſed; and there are determined Writs of Appeals, and other Writs upon criminal Actions, and injuries <hi>contra pacem.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:62733:19"/>
               <p>He hath alſo his Courts and his Juſtices reſiding in the <hi>Exchequer,</hi> and alſo in <hi>Banco</hi> (now called the <hi>Common-Pleas</hi>) at <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> and ſome are aſſign'd for Gaol-deliveries in every County, and ſome are affign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to take Aſſizes generally in every County, and ſome are itenerant, and conſtituted to hear and determine all criminal and civil Pleas. Alſo, the King hath his Juſtices itenerant, to hear and determine the Pleas of the Foreſt; and he hath his Court in eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry County, and in the Sheriffs Turn, and in Hundreds, and in the King's Manors, Cities and Boroughs, as in the Huſtings of <hi>London, Lincoln, Wincheſter, York,</hi> and other places.</p>
               <p>And the ſame Author having afterwards treat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed more particularly of what Juriſdiction the King had de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legated to every Court,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Fleta</hi> l 2. f. 75. cap. 33.</note> he writes thus of the Chancery: <hi>There is, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the rest, a certain Office called the</hi> Chancery, <hi>which ought to be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:62733:19"/>to the care of ſome prudent man, as a Biſhop, or Clergy man of great dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, together with the care of the great Seal of</hi> England, <hi>under whom are all the Chancellors in</hi> England, Ireland, Wales <hi>and</hi> Scotland, <hi>and all Keepers of the Kings Seals, (except the Keeper of the Privy Seal) to whom are aſſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciated</hi> Clerici honeſti, <hi>honest and circumſpect Clerks, ſworn to our Lord the King, and who in the Laws and Customs of</hi> England <hi>have ample knowledge; whoſe Office it is to hear and examine the Complaints of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plainants, and to grant due remedy by the King's Writ, according to the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and quality of the wrong.</hi> And there he treats at large of the Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers, Clerks, and Buſineſs of the Chancery, which was to make out Remedial or Original Writs, and Judicial Writs, alſo upon Recogni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zances and Contracts made in the Chancery, and enroll'd there: but not one tittle or mention is there made by any of the ſaid Authors, of
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:62733:20"/>any Superiority the Lord Chancel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lor or Lord Keeper; or the Court of Chancery had over the Proceedings of any of the other Judges, either to examine, correct, or rectifie their Judgments, or ſtop execution there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, upon any account, colour or pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence whatſoever; which is a moſt convincing proof, the Chancellor then had no ſuch power.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="section">
               <head>SECT. III. What <hi>is meant by</hi> Judging ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to Equity; <hi>and by</hi> Whom <hi>it was anciently per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>HAving laid the foundation of my preſent purpoſe upon what I find in the fore-mention'd Authors, I think it not amiſs to ſay ſomewhat touching their credit; and firſt of all, that which gives them a reputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion with me, is, that they ſet down
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:62733:20"/>what they themſelves of their own knowledge knew to be true; they relate what the Law was at the time of the writing of thoſe Books, they took nothing upon truſt from other hands, but ſet down what they them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves knew to be practice. Next, they were men of great Eminency; <hi>Bra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cton</hi> was a learned Judge, and it was his zeal to Juſtice induc'd him to write; <hi>Britton</hi> was a Book writ by the King's own command, and pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh'd by his approbation; and the others, <hi>Mirror</hi> and <hi>Fleta,</hi> have al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways had a great reputation amongſt the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Lawyers, not only anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent, but modern; and Sir <hi>Edward Cooke,</hi> who once was honour'd with the title of <hi>the Oracle of the Law,</hi> in his firſt <hi>Inſtitutes,</hi> in every page al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt quotes thoſe Authors for proof of his aſſertions; and ſo doth <hi>Stan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford</hi> in his <hi>Pleas of the Crown:</hi> from whence I conclude, that what they wrote for Law, was Law <hi>then;</hi> and if ſo, it is Law <hi>now,</hi> ſaving wherein<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>it
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:62733:21"/>it is alter'd by the Kings Parliamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary Act; nothing leſs than That could change the Law.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Bracton,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Bract.</hi> f. 3.</note> ſpeaking of Equity, ſays, <hi>Equitas autem eſt rerum canveniontia quae in paribus cauſis paria deſiderat Jura, &amp; omnia bene coaequiparat:</hi> It is a certain ſort of accord and congruity in things, which affects the like Judgments in like Caſes, and equally and indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rently conſiders all circumſtances. Equity is that Right which ariſes and appears upon a due conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the written Law, the circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances of the matter in queſtion, and that natural Juſtice which a good conſcience dictates, and to judge and determine the matter according<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, I take to be a <hi>judging according to Equity.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It ſhould ſeem that all the Judges mentioned by the ſaid Authors,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Eritt.</hi> ſo. 1.</note> were ty'd to proceed and judge according to preſcribed Rules; for by <hi>Britton</hi> it appears,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:62733:21"/>that it was the King's will the Laws (which are Rules) ſhould be ſet in writing, and uſed and kept in every point, ſaving to himſelf, with con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent of his Counts, Barons, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer to repeal and amend them; but it belong'd to himſelf alone, princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pally and in chief to amend falſe Judgments of his Juſtices generally, as appears by this; <hi>Car ceo reſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>douns nous eſpecialment a noſtre Juriſdiction.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The King's command to uſe the Laws and Rules in every point ſtrict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, was general to all his Judges; but it was only He that had power in all his Judgments to regard Equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>above Rules; and he had not only <hi>power</hi> ſo to do,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Bract.</hi> lib. 3. fo. 107.</note> but he was <hi>oblig'd</hi> to it by the latter part of the Coronation-Oath before-recited.
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Bract.</hi> lib. 2. fo. 24.</note> It was the King only had an extraordinary Prehemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nence over the preſcribed Rules and
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:62733:22"/>Forms of Law, to moderate the ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gour and extremity, and ſupply the defects thereof upon occaſion, when his Judges could not exceed the Rules preſcribed them; and this power is as neceſſary as any thing can be for the right diſtribution of Juſtice; for it is impoſſible to make ſuch Rules before-hand, as may ſuit with all caſes; for an extraordinary circumſtance may ſometimes happen in ſome caſes, that to judge thereof according to general and preſcribed Rules of Law, might be to wrong the party, and ſo make <hi>ſummum jus, ſumma injuria.</hi> But our ancient Kings did not entruſt this Power at any time, as I find, with any ſingle perſon:
<note place="margin">Elſ. Office, ch. fo. 25.</note> For, during the Reign of both the <hi>Willi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ams, Henry</hi> 1. King <hi>Ste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phen,</hi> and <hi>Henry</hi> 2, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> until <hi>Ed.</hi> 3's. time at leaſtwiſe,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Dud.</hi> Orig. Jud. fo. 25.</note> if not after, there ſtill continu'd a particular Court be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing to che King, which was the
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:62733:22"/>place of Sovereign Juſtice, both for matters of Law and Equity, called <hi>Curia Domini Regis,</hi> and <hi>Aula Regia,</hi> or <hi>magna Curia,</hi> where He himſelf oftentimes ſate in perſon; but there he had his Juſtices <hi>à latere ſuo ſeden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes;</hi> as namely, his Chief-Juſtice, his Chancellor, his Conſtable and Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhal, and ſuch others of his Nobles as the King pleas'd to aſſociate to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf for that purpoſe: The Juſtice, to inform the King of what was the ſtrict Rules of Law;
<note place="margin">Capital' Juſtic' praeſider primus a Rege in Regno C. 4. int' fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> to Cancellarii <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliae</hi> Dignitas eſt ut ſecundes a Rege in Regno habeatur, ibidem. fol. 78.</note> and the Chancellor, who was uſually a ſpiritual man, to give advice ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to Equity, and there matters of Equity were then determined; And to this Court any man might appeal from the inferiour Courts, to have the Errors of the Judges cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected and amended; and if the King were abſent, the Juſticiar was
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:62733:23"/>the King's chief Repreſentative.</p>
               <p>But when it was that firſt the Chancellor had that power of judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing according to Equity ſo given him that he alone could do it of courſe, is not certainly known.</p>
               <p>Some ſuppoſe,
<note place="margin">Orig. Ind. fol. 36. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>Lamb. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap>.</hi>
                  </note> that in <hi>Ed.</hi> 1. 's time, when the Power of the <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticiarius Anglia</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clin'd, the King, together with the Great Seal, entruſted the Chancellor with his own extraordinary prehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minence of Juriſdiction over the Common Law, <hi>viz. Power of judging according to Equity:</hi> but that Authors reaſon is not ſufficient to maintain that ſuppoſition; for he gives no reaſon for it, but <hi>that be finds no mention made of any ſuch power in the</hi> Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cery <hi>by</hi> Britton; which was wrote about the beginning of the Reign of <hi>E.</hi> 1. Yet <hi>Britton</hi> mentions the Juriſdiction of all the other Courts, and he concludes from thence, <hi>that if the</hi> Chancellors <hi>had then had any
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:62733:23"/>ſuch power,</hi> Britton <hi>would have menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned it:</hi> which indeed is a good ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument that the Chancellor had no ſuch power then, but it doth not fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low of conſequence, that becauſe he had it not when <hi>Britton</hi> was writ, that he muſt needs have it immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately thereupon: therefore we muſt come a little, yea a great way nea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer, before we can find this power fixed in the Chancellor alone.</p>
               <p>No doubt but when the <hi>Juſticiari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us Angliae</hi> was laid aſide, the Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellor, who before that time was but <hi>ſecundus à Rege in Regno,</hi> became then <hi>primus à Rege,</hi> and was Preſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent over the reſt when any matter of Law or Equity was determined in <hi>magna Curia,</hi> in the abſence of the King; but I cannot find he exerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the Judicative power in mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of Equity alone, until very late<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, tho' he did ſeveral other things alone. I find,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>G.</hi> 4. Inſt. fo. 83. Mag. Cha. 553.</note> that in <hi>R.</hi> 2.'s time a matter being compromited by
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:62733:24"/>both ſides to the King, the King re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred it to the Councel, and they make a Decree, which Decree was ſent to the Chancellor to confirm un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Great Seal, which was done; after which one of the parties petiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned the King that the matter might be left to the determination of the Common-Law; whereupon the King, by warrant under the Privy-Seal, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires the Chancellor to make <hi>Super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſedeas</hi> to the Decree, which was done: whereby it appears, the Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellor alone did nothing but award Proceſs upon the Decree made by the Councel, as the King and They directed. <hi>And this,</hi> Sir <hi>Edw. Cooke</hi> ſays, <hi>was the firſt Decree in</hi> Chancery <hi>that ever he obſerved in all his read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>He alſo cites ſome opinions,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Cooke</hi>'s Magna. Charta. 553.</note> that the Court of Equity in Chancery began under <hi>Henry Beaufort</hi> Son of <hi>Jo.</hi> of <hi>Gaunt,</hi> who was Chancellor in the beginning of <hi>H.</hi> 6.'s time; and his
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:62733:24"/>reaſon for it is, <hi>becauſe there is not in any Book-Caſe, or Report of the Law, any mention made of any</hi> Court of Equity <hi>held before the</hi> Chancellors, <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Reign of</hi> H. 6. <hi>and yet all of them ſpeak of the ordinary Power and Juriſdiction of the</hi> Chancery: But in the Reign of <hi>H.</hi> 6. and <hi>E.</hi> 4. Caſes have been reported to have been de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termined in Chancery, according to Equity; but it is obſervable, that moſt of thoſe Cauſes were heard before ſeveral others, together with the Chancellor; and that in matters of doubt, he adjourn'd the patties into the <hi>Exchequer-Chamber</hi> before himſelf and the Juſtices of both Ben<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, and made his Decrees accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to their Opinion: As for in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance; In the Year-book of the 37th. of <hi>H.</hi> 6. fo. 13. the Caſe was, <hi>That one</hi> A. <hi>had bought of</hi> J. R. <hi>ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Debts due to</hi> J. R. <hi>from ſeveral per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, and</hi> A. <hi>gave a Bond to</hi> J. R. <hi>for the ſum; And foraſmuch as thoſe Debts were but things in Action, and
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:62733:25"/>no Property was chang'd, nor no Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on accru'd by the bargain to the ſaid</hi> A. <hi>but the Debtors remained Debtors ſtill to the ſaid</hi> J. R. <hi>ſo that</hi> A. <hi>had nothing for the money ſecured by the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligation.</hi> A. <hi>prays in Equity to be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charged of the ſaid Bond againſt</hi> J.R. <hi>and prays a</hi> Subpaena <hi>againſt</hi> J.R. <hi>and it was granted, and the Defendant anſwered, and the</hi> Chancellor, <hi>becauſe the matter ſeemed doubtful to him, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>journ'd it to the</hi> Exchequer-Chamber <hi>before himſelf and the Justices of both Benches, and there it was debated, and by the Opinion of all the Juſtices, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the ſaid</hi> A. <hi>had not</hi> quid pro quo <hi>by that bargain, therefore the Bond ought to be releaſed, and it was decreed accordingly.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The like will appear to be done by the Book-caſes following, 37 <hi>H.</hi> 6. f. 35, 36, 39 <hi>H.</hi> 6. f. 26.7 <hi>E.</hi> 4. f. 14, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And if he did not adjourn the Cauſes into the <hi>Exchequer-Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber,</hi> he always had the Judges, or ſome of them, with him at all hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings,
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:62733:25"/>and decreed according to their Opinions; for the entry of the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crees in Chancery of <hi>H.</hi> 6.'s time are after this manner,
<note place="margin">Elſ. Off. of Chan. fo. 51.</note> ſays the Author cited in the Margin, <hi>viz. Conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratum est per Curiam ex aſſenſu</hi> Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hannis Forteſcue <hi>Milit' Capital' Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sticiar' Domini Regis ad placita te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nenda &amp; diverſorum aliorum Justicia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riorum &amp; ſervient' ad legem in Curia praeſent' exiſtent' quod, &amp;c.</hi> and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times it was, <hi>ex aſſenſu omnium Justi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciar' utriuſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> Banci,</hi> and ſometimes of one or two Juſtices; but before the end of that King's Reign, the manner of entry of the Decrees was ſomewhat altered, and was in this manner; <hi>Conſiderat' Adjudicatum &amp; Decret' eſt per</hi> Cancellarium <hi>&amp; per Curiam</hi> Cancellar', without particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar mention of any Juſtices or others, and ſo it continued till <hi>H.</hi> 8.'s time; But towards the end of his Reign, whereas before that time the Decrees were in <hi>Latine,</hi> and in very few
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:62733:26"/>words, and entred on the back-ſide of the Bills, they then began to be drawn up in <hi>Engliſh</hi> apart by them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and therein reciting the Bill and Anſwer, and afterward were en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roll'd in Rolls by themſelves: The ancienteſt of that nature that I can find, are in the Rolls Chappel, and are of the 27th. and 28th. of <hi>H.</hi> 8. when Sir <hi>Thomas Audley</hi> was Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellor. In Queen <hi>Maries</hi> days the entry of all the Decrees is, <hi>That it is Ordained, Adjudged and Decreed by the Lord</hi> Chancellor, <hi>and by the whole</hi> Court of Chancery, <hi>That ſo and ſo:</hi> and after the ſame manner it is at this day, ſaving that the conjunctive clauſe <hi>And by the High-Court of Chancery,</hi> (which in the beginning was not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certed in vain) is now altogether ſuperfluous and impertinent; for the Lord Chancellor or Lord Keeper, without the aſſent or conſent of any other, have made Decrees for ſome years paſt according to his own <hi>libe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum arbitrium,</hi> as I ſhall ſhew in the next Section.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="section">
               <pb n="43" facs="tcp:62733:26"/>
               <head>SECT. IV. <hi>Of the modern and preſent Power and Juriſdiction of the Court of Equity in</hi> Chancery.</head>
               <p>IN the <hi>Chancery</hi> are two Courts,
<note place="margin">C. 4. Inſt. fo. 79.</note> one Ordinary, wherein the Lord Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellor or Lord Keeper of the Great Seals proceeds according to the right line of the Law, and if he gives an Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roneous Judgement,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Plowd.</hi> 393. que <hi>B.R.</hi> eſt le Pluis hault. Court. <hi>Dyer</hi> 315.</note> there a Writ of Error lies returnable in the <hi>Kings Bench;</hi> the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is Extraordinary, wherein the Chancellor ought to proceed according to the Rule of Equity, which according to what it is now taken, is what is according to the Chancellor's ſingle Conſcience,
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:62733:27"/>
                  <hi>quecun<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan>
                     <note place="margin">Elſ. Office of <hi>Ch.</hi> fo. 41.</note> ſit;</hi> it is (ſay ſome,) an abſolute Power without con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troul, other then in Parliament, and ſpreadeth it ſelf moſt largely with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any Limitation, it ſtops the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings of all the other Courts at <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> it renders all their Judgements vain and ineffectual, <hi>durante bene placito,</hi> of the Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellor or Keeper, and ſtops Execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, untill his Conſcience be ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied whether the Plaintiffs at Law ought to go on or no, by which means when a man hath a Judgement fairly obtain'd at Law, or intends to Sue there for a Juſt and True Debt, if the Defendant at Law becomes Plaintiff in <hi>Chancery,</hi> and he or his Councel hath but Invention enough to ſuggeſt any ſort of Equity, there's an Injunction had of courſe, until the Plaintiff at Law can put an An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer to the Bill; which if he lives any thing remote from <hi>London,</hi> it will take up a Month or two's time,
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:62733:27"/>or more, to ſend an Anſwer, and in the mean time the Debtor prepares his Bag and Baggage, and by that time the Injunction can be Diſſolv'd, which cannot be without a conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rabe Charge, the Gentlemen is per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps got to <hi>Ireland, Jamaico</hi> or <hi>Japan.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>What ever is now finally deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>min'd in Equity in <hi>Chancery,</hi> it is done by the Chancellor or Lord Keeper alone, and though the Clerks and Regiſters retain in drawing up their Decrees ſomewhat of the old form, <hi>ziz. That it is Decreed by the Lord Chancellor or Lord Keeper, and by the High Court of</hi> Chancery; which implyes there were ſome o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers ought to have a hand in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king the Decree; yet there is none that now have, for though there are two at leaſt of twelve that bear the name of Maſters in <hi>Chancery;</hi> and heretofore were accounted <hi>Socii</hi> and <hi>Collaterales</hi> to the Chancellor that daily ſit in Court one on each ſide
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:62733:28"/>of the Lord Chancellor or Keeper; yet they are now but as his Atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dants, and ſpeak not a word in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termining any Cauſes, their only buſineſs being to wait and expect how many References the Lord Chancellor will make to them touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing inſufficient Anſwers, Scandalous Bills or Anſwers, Contempts, ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of Accounts and the like, they being to have a Fee for their Report therein, yet that Report is ſubject to the controul of the Chancellor or Keeper, if he pleaſes; And if at any time, which is but ſeldom, any of the Judges are ſent for, it often proves to be meerly out of Forma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, for their Opinions are ſeldom regarded.</p>
               <p>It is ſaid of the Chancellor and Keeper of the Great-Seal of <hi>England,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Elſ. Office of <hi>Cla</hi> fo. 6.</note> that he is like the <hi>Roman Praetor,</hi> in whoſe Conſtitutions there were ſaid to be two kinds of Powers; one was, when without
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:62733:28"/>the Advice of the Judges he would Manumittiſe, Emancipate, Award Poſſeſſions of Lands and Goods, Commit Wardſhip of Pupills, and grant Injunctions as he thought con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venient: The other ſort of Power the <hi>Praetor</hi> had, was when he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded to Judgment according to <hi>Leges Regis,</hi> &amp;c. The Kings Laws, the Laws of the Twelve Tables, the Civil Law, Laws made by the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent of the People, or Decrees of the Senate, and therein he was not abſolute as in the other: But out Chancellor or Keeper and their <hi>Prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor</hi> do do differ very much, for the <hi>Praetor</hi> would at his Entry into that Office propound and publiſh certain Edicts, which were Principles and Fountains out of which he would derive his Decrees; but what Rules or General Notions the Lord Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellor or Lord Keeper in <hi>England</hi> doth aſſign unto himſelf for Limita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Equity, and direction of his Conſcience, thoſe lie hid and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cealed
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:62733:29"/>in his own Breaſt, ſo that neither the Man of Law nor Equity is able to inform his Client what is like to become of the Cauſe, and conſequently no man is able to know what is his own, ſo that it may be ſaid of this great Officer arm'd with this great Power, as was ſaid of <hi>Jeremiah</hi>'s Figs;
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Jer.</hi> 24.4.</note> 
                  <hi>Thoſe that were good, were very good; but thoſe that were evil, were exceeding evil:</hi> For that Power if it be uſed according to the true intent and deſign of it, is of Excellent uſe,
<note place="margin">Optima corrupta ſunt peſſima.</note> but if a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus'd, it is the greateſt oppreſſion imaginable; and that that Power hath been a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſed, will appear by the next Section.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="section">
               <pb n="49" facs="tcp:62733:29"/>
               <head>SECT. V. <hi>Of the</hi> Corruptions <hi>and</hi> Miſtakes <hi>of ſome Great</hi> Chancellors.</head>
               <p>I Find in the Journal Book of the Lords Houſe in the year 1620. and in the 19th. year of King <hi>James,</hi> that on the 19th. of <hi>March</hi> in that year, a Meſſage was ſent from the Lower Houſe to the Lords, importing; <hi>That they had found Abuſes in certain Eminent Perſons, about which they deſired a Conference with their Lordſhips, that ſuch courſe might be taken, as might ſtand with the Honour and Dignity of a Parliament;</hi> which was agreed to by the Lords, and the Conference was appointed to be that afternoon; and the next day it was Reported to the Lords by the Lord Treaſurer: <hi>That at the Conference was deliver'd the deſire of the Commons to inform their Lordſhips
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:62733:30"/>what they had found in their Inquiry after the Abuſes of the Courts of Juſtice,</hi> where, after having highly com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended the incomparable good parts of the then Lord Chancellor, and magnified his place from whence Bounty, Juſtice and Mercy were to be diſtributed to the Subject, with which he was wholly Intruſted: <hi>They declared that the Lord Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellor was Accuſed of great Bribery and Corruption committed by him;</hi> And inſtanced two Caſes, one con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning one <hi>Chriſtopher Awbrey,</hi> and the other concerning one <hi>Edward Egerton:</hi> As to <hi>Awbrey,</hi> the matter was, <hi>That He having a Cauſe in</hi> Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cery <hi>between Him and Sir</hi> William Brunker, Awbrey <hi>feeling ſome hard meaſure, was advis'd to give the Lord</hi> Chancellor 100 l. <hi>which he deliver'd to his Council Sir</hi> John Haſtings, <hi>and He to the</hi> Chancellor; <hi>but notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, the buſineſs proceeding ſlow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,</hi> Awbrey <hi>writ ſeveral Letters, and deliver'd them to the Lord</hi> Chancellor,
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:62733:30"/>
                  <hi>but could never have any Anſwer from his Lordſhip; but at laſt delivering another Letter, his Lordſhip told him, if he importun'd him, he would lay him by the Heels:</hi> As to <hi>Egerton</hi>'s matter, it was ſet out at large at the Conference; and will appear by the ſubſtance of <hi>Egerton</hi>'s Petition to the Lords, the effect whereof (amongſt other things,) is as follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth; <hi>That the ſaid</hi> Edward Egerton <hi>being <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nmarried and Sickly, he ſettled his Eſtate to the uſe of himſelf and the Heirs Males of his Body, and for default of ſuch Iſſue, the Remainder to Sir</hi> John Egerton <hi>and his Heirs, which Settlement was voluntarily made, without any conſideration paid for the ſame, and with Power of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocation; and that Sir</hi> Rowland Egerton, <hi>Son and Heir of the ſaid Sir</hi> John Egerton, <hi>had got the ſaid Settlement into his hands, and all the Petitioners Writings; and that the late Lord Chancellor</hi> Elſemere <hi>had Decreed, that Sir</hi> Rowland Egerton
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:62733:31"/>
                  <hi>ſhould have the manner of</hi> Wrinehal <hi>and</hi> Haywood Barnes, <hi>being a great part of the Petitioners Inheritance, worth</hi> 600 l. per Annum, <hi>without any cauſe of Equity contain'd in the ſaid Decree; and that the Petitioner had made humble Suit to the Lord Viſcount St.</hi> Albans, <hi>then Lord Chancellor of</hi> England, <hi>to have the benefit of a Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, to recover his Ancient Inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance by Ordinary courſe of Law; and that his Lordſhip took from the Peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioner</hi> 400 l. <hi>in Gold, and</hi> 52 l. 10 s. <hi>in Silver Plate, which Money was accepted of by the ſaid Lord Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellor, ſaying withall, That the Peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioner had not only Enrich'd him, but laid a tye upon him to do the Peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioner Juſtice in his Rightful Cauſes, and by great Oaths and Proteſtations drew the Petitioner to Seal an Obliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to his Lordſhip of ten thouſand</hi> Marks, <hi>to ſtand to his Lordſhips Award; and that afterwards the Peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioner was divers times ſent for by one</hi> Robert Sharpeigh, <hi>then Steward of
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:62733:31"/>his Lordſhips Houſhold; and that the Petitioner was ſeveral times offer'd, that if he would then preſently pay</hi> 1100 l. <hi>in ready Money, that is to ſay,</hi> 1000 l. <hi>to his Lordſhip, and</hi> 100 l. <hi>to</hi> Sharpeigh, <hi>the Petitioner ſhould have all his Lands Decreed to him, which Money he could not readi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly pay; and that afterwards the ſaid Lord Chancellor did not only confirm unto the ſaid Sir</hi> Rowland Egerton, <hi>the Land which he then held of the ſaid Petitioner's Inheritance, being worth</hi> 600 l. per Annum, <hi>but took a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way more Lands worth</hi> 15000 l. <hi>and Decreed the ſame to Sir</hi> Rowland Egerton, <hi>who did not claim any Title thereto, before the ſaid Bond taken, and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nlawful Decree made; and that he alſo Decreed the Bond ſhould be Aſſigned to Sir</hi> Rowland Egerton: <hi>And the Petitioner having ſpent</hi> 600 l. <hi>in Suits, and being depriv'd of all his Evidences by the ſaid Lord Chancel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lor, and by the indirect practice of the ſaid Sir</hi> Rowland: <hi>He was likely to
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:62733:32"/>be utterly defrauded of all his Anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Inheritance, contrary to the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Juſtice of the Land, unleſs re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liev'd by their Lordſhips.</hi> The Contents of which Petition, the Petitioner made Oath to be true; and he and <hi>Sharpeigh</hi> were fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Examin'd touching the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</p>
               <p>By the Journal of the Lords Houſe for the 21ſt. of <hi>March,</hi> in the year 1600. It appears that there had been Information given to the Houſe, that there had been a Cauſe depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding in <hi>Chancery</hi> between one <hi>Smith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wicke</hi> and <hi>Wiche,</hi> which was matter of Account, and had been Referred to Merchants, and the Merchants had Certified on <hi>Smithwick</hi>'s behalf; yet to obtain a Decree in the Cauſe, he was told by one <hi>Burrough,</hi> (that was near to the Lord Chancellor) that it muſt coſt him 200 <hi>l.</hi> which he paid to the uſe of the Lord Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellor; yet his Lordſhip Decreed but one part of the Certificate:
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:62733:32"/>Whereupon he treats again with <hi>Burrough,</hi> who demands another 100 <hi>l.</hi> which <hi>Smithwick</hi> alſo paid to the uſe of the Lord Chancellor; then his Lordſhip Referr'd the Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counts again to the Merchants, who Certified again for <hi>Smithwick,</hi> yet his Lordſhip Decreed the ſecond part of the Certificate againſt <hi>Smith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wick;</hi> and the firſt part, which was formerly Decreed for him, his Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip made doubtful: whereupon <hi>Smithwick</hi> Petition'd to the Lord Chancellor to have his Money again, and he had it.</p>
               <p>It appears further by the ſaid Journal Books, that ſeveral days were in a great part Employed in taking Examination of Witneſſes in proving and detecting the Briberies and Corruptions of that Lord Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellor; which being ended and col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected, were order'd to be Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcrib'd with the Proofs; and on the 24th. of <hi>April</hi> following were order'd to be ſent to his Lordſhip, with a
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:62733:33"/>Meſſage that the Lords requir'd his Anſwer with all convenient ſpeed.</p>
               <p>The Corruptions, as they are men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned to be prov'd in the Journal of the Lords Houſe of the ſaid 24th. of <hi>April,</hi> are as followeth:
<list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>That in the Cauſe between Sir</hi> Rowland Egerton <hi>and</hi> Edward Egerton, <hi>his Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip received on the part of Sir</hi> Rowland Egerton <hi>before he decreed for him,</hi> — 500 l.</item>
                     <item>Item, <hi>of</hi> Edward Egerton <hi>in the ſaid Cauſe,</hi> — 400 l.</item>
                     <item>Item, <hi>in the Cauſe between</hi> Hodie <hi>and</hi> Hodie, <hi>a dozen of Buttons (after the Cauſe end ed) of the value of</hi> — 50 l.</item>
                     <item>Item, <hi>of the Lady</hi> Wharton, 310 l.</item>
                     <item>Item, <hi>of Sir</hi> Tho. Munke, 100 l.</item>
                     <item>Item, <hi>of Sir</hi> John Trevor, 100 l.</item>
                     <item>Item, <hi>of one</hi> Young, — 100 l.</item>
                     <item>Item, <hi>of one</hi> Fiſher, — 106 l.</item>
                     <item>Item, <hi>in the Cauſe of</hi> Ken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day <hi>and</hi> Valore, <hi>of</hi> Kenday <hi>a Cabinet worth</hi> — 800 l.</item>
                     <pb n="57" facs="tcp:62733:33"/>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Of</hi> Valore <hi>(borrow'd at two times)</hi> — 2000 l.</item>
                     <item>Item, <hi>in the Cauſe between</hi> Scot <hi>and</hi> Lenthall, <hi>of</hi> Scot — 200 l.</item>
                     <item>Item, <hi>of</hi> Lenthall, — 100 l.</item>
                     <item>Item, <hi>of one</hi> Wroth, <hi>who had a Cauſe between him and one</hi> Mannering, — 100 l.</item>
                     <item>Item, <hi>of Sir</hi> Ralph Hansby, 500 l.</item>
                     <item>Item, <hi>in the Lord</hi> Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine<hi>'s Cauſe, of the Lord</hi> Mountaine, <hi>and more promis'd at the end of the Cauſe,</hi> — 600 or 700 l.</item>
                     <item>Item, <hi>of one Mr.</hi> Dunch, — 200 l.</item>
                     <item>Item, <hi>in a Cauſe between</hi> Raynold <hi>and</hi> Peacock, 200 <hi>l. in money, and a Diamond Ring worth</hi> 5 <hi>or</hi> 600 <hi>l.</hi> — 700 or 800 l.</item>
                     <item>Item, <hi>of</hi> Peacock, — 100 l.</item>
                     <item>Item, <hi>in a Cauſe of</hi> Barker, 700 l.</item>
                     <item>Item, <hi>there being a reference from his Majeſty to his Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of a buſineſs between the Grocers and Apothecaries, he had of the Grocers</hi> — 200 l.</item>
                     <pb n="58" facs="tcp:62733:34"/>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Of the Apothecaries, (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides a rich preſent of Amber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greece)</hi> — 150 l.</item>
                     <item>Item, <hi>of the</hi> French <hi>Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants, to constrain the Vint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners of</hi> London <hi>to take</hi> 1500 <hi>Tuns of Wine; to accompliſh which, he uſed very indirect means, by colour of his Office and Authority, without Bill or other Suit depending, as threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning and impriſoning the Vint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, for which he receiv'd of the Merchants</hi> — 1000 l.</item>
                     <item>Laſtly, <hi>That he had given way to great exactions by his Servants, in reſpect of private Seals, and ſealing In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junctions.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>By the Journal-book of the 25th. of the ſaid month it appears, that Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron <hi>Denham</hi> and Mr. Attorney-Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral reported their delivery of the Charge of the Lord Chancellors cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptions to his Lordſhip, and that he ſaid he would return the Lords an
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:62733:34"/>Anſwer: whereupon the Lords ſoon after ſent a meſſage by Baron <hi>Den<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> and Mr. Attorney, to know if he would make his Confeſſion, or ſtand to his Defence; to which they brought anſwer, That his Lordſhip would make no defence to the charge, but meant to acknowledge corruption, and to make a particular confeſſion to every point, and after that, an humble ſubmiſſion; but he humbly crav'd liberty, that wherein the charge was more full than he finds the truth of the Fact, he may make declaration of the truth in ſuch particulars; the charge being brief, and not containing all circumſtances: Whereupon the Lords ſent the ſame Meſſengers back to him, to let him know, they had granted him time till <hi>Monday</hi> next, being the 30th. of <hi>April,</hi> at 10 in the morning to ſend ſuch Confeſſion as his Lordſhip in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended to make.</p>
               <p>On the 30th. of <hi>April</hi> the Lord Chief-Juſtice <hi>Leigh</hi> (who then exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:62733:35"/>the place of Lord Chancellor) in the Lords Houſe, ſignified to their Lordſhips, that he had received a Letter and paper Roll ſealed up; which being delivered to the Clark of the Lords Houſe, and being ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, &amp; found directed to their Lord ſhips, it was read, and began thus:</p>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="deposition">
                  <body>
                     <head>
                        <hi>To the Right Honourable the Lords Spiritual and Temporal, in the High-Court of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment aſſembled.</hi> The Confeſſion and humble Submiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of Me the Lord Chancellor.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>UPon adviſed conſideration of the charge, deſcending into my own conſcience, and calling my memory to an account ſo far as I am able: I do plainly and ingeniouſly confeſs, that I am guilty of Corruption; and do re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce all defence, and put my ſelf upon the Grace and Mercy of your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <pb n="61" facs="tcp:62733:35"/>
                     <p>The particulars I do confeſs, and declare to be as followeth:</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>To the firſt Article of the charge,</hi> viz. <hi>in the Cauſe between Sir</hi> Rowland Egerton <hi>and</hi> Edward Egerton, <hi>the Lord Chancellor received</hi> 500 l. <hi>on the part of Sir</hi> Rowland Egerton <hi>before he decreed the Cauſe: I do confeſs and declare,</hi> Upon a reference from his Majeſty of all Suits and Controver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies between Sir <hi>Rowland Egerton</hi> and Mr. <hi>Edward Egerton,</hi> both parties ſubmitted to my award by Recog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nizance reciprocally in 10000 Marks apiece, and thereupon after divers hearings, I made my award with ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice and conſent of my Lord <hi>Hobbart,</hi> and the award was perfected and publiſh'd to the parties, which was in <hi>February;</hi> Then ſome days after the 500 <hi>l.</hi> mentioned in the charge was delivered to me; Afterwards Mr. <hi>Edward Egerton</hi> fled from the award; Then in <hi>Midſummer</hi> Term following a Suit was begun in <hi>Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cery</hi> by Sir <hi>Rowland,</hi> to have the
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:62733:36"/>award confirm'd; and upon that Suit was the Decree made, which is mention'd in this Article.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>To the ſecond Article,</hi> viz. <hi>That in the ſame Cauſe he received from</hi> Edw. Egerton 400 l. <hi>I confeſs and declare,</hi> That ſoon after my firſt coming to the Seal, (being a time when I was preſented by many) the 400 <hi>l.</hi> men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned in the charge was delivered unto me in a Purſe, and I now call to mind from Mr. <hi>Edward Egerton:</hi> But, as far as I can remember, it was expreſt by him that brought it to be for <hi>favours past,</hi> and not in reſpect of <hi>favours to come.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>To the third Article of the charge,</hi> viz. <hi>in the Cauſe between</hi> Hodie <hi>and</hi> Hodie, <hi>he receiv'd a dozen of Buttons of the value of</hi> 50 l. <hi>about a fortnight after the Cauſe was ended: I confeſs and declare,</hi> That, as it is laid in the charge, about a fortnight after the Cauſe was ended (it being a Suit of great Inheritance) there were Gold Buttons about the value of 50 <hi>l.</hi> (as
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:62733:36"/>is mentioned in the charge) preſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted unto me, as I remember, by Sir <hi>John Perient</hi> and the party himſelf.</p>
                     <p>Thus far it is <hi>verbatim</hi> as it is in the ſaid Journal book; and after the ſame form he proceeds, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſeth the receipt of all the money and other things in the charge, and ſome particular ſums more, but with ſome little endeavours to extenuate the Crime; as, <hi>that the money was ſent as a preſent after the Cauſes ended;</hi> and confeſſed, <hi>that he had impriſoned ſome of the Vintners, becauſe they refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to take off the</hi> French <hi>Wines; and that it was a great fault in him that he look'd not after his Servants.</hi> And then follows theſe words, <hi>viz. This Declaration I have made to your Lordſhips with a ſincere mind, humbly craving, that if there ſhould be any miſtake, your Lordſhips would impute it to want of memory, and not to any deſign of mine to obſcure truth, or to palliate any thing; for I do again confeſs, that in the points charg'd upon
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:62733:37"/>me, although they ſhould be taken as my ſelf have declared, there's a great deal of corruption and neglect; for which I am heartily and penitently ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and ſubmit my ſelf to the Judgment, Grace and Mercy of this Court.</hi> And in the cloſe he prays, <hi>That if they pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed to a Sentence, their Sentence may not be too heavy.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <p>The Confeſſion being read, the Lords ſent twelve Lords to know if it was his own hand that ſubſcrib'd the Confeſſion, and whether he would ſtand to it, or no? and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing returned, they report, That they had ſhew'd it to him, and that he own'd it, and would abide by it: Whereupon it was ordered, That the Prince (attended by ſome of the Lords) ſhould move His Majeſty to ſequeſter the Seal; which being ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly done, the Prince reports to the Houſe, That he had mov'd the King therein, and that his Majeſty had promis'd it ſhould be done, and that he intended to have done it if they had not mov'd it.</p>
               <pb n="65" facs="tcp:62733:37"/>
               <p>The ſecond of <hi>May</hi> following a Commiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on was granted to Sir <hi>James Leigh</hi> Chief Juſtice,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Vid. Rot.</hi> Parl. <hi>ejuſdem temp.</hi>
                  </note> to Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciate the place of the Lord Chancel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lor in the Lords Houſe; and the Great Seal was taken from the Chancellor,
<note place="margin">There was not a ſingle Lord keeper from that time until the 10 of <hi>July</hi> 1621. the Buſineſs of the <hi>Chancery</hi> being then performed by the Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſioners.</note> and by Commiſſion committed to be kept by the Lord Treaſurer, the Lord Steward, the Lord. Chamberlain, and the Earl of <hi>Arun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dell.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The third of <hi>May</hi> the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons ſent a Meſſage to the Lords to demand Judgment againſt the Lord Chancellor, to which the Lords re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn'd anſwer; they were ready, if They with their <hi>Speaker</hi> would come to demand it; and the <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons</hi> being come to the Bar of the Lords Houſe, the Chief Juſtice <hi>Leigh</hi> pronounc'd the Judgment, which was,</p>
               <pb n="66" facs="tcp:62733:38"/>
               <p n="1">1ſt. <hi>That the Lord Viſcount St.</hi> Albans <hi>ſhould undergo a Fine and Ranſome of</hi> 40000 l.</p>
               <p n="2">2d. <hi>That he ſhould be Impriſon'd in the</hi> Tower <hi>during the Kings pleaſure.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3d. <hi>That he ſhould be for ever un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>capable of any Office, Place or Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployment in the State or Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4th. <hi>That he ſhould never ſit in Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, nor come within the Verge of the Court.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I have been more particular in relating theſe proceedings of the late Lord Chancellor <hi>Bacon,</hi> becauſe of the great Learning and Eminency of the Man, and the little need he had to be ſo Corrupt, he had nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Wife nor Child to provide for; and if ſuch a man was guilty of Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bery and Corruption, who may we be ſure will not? And therefore great care ought to be taken to have Relief againſt ſuch contingencies; for Corruption in a Judge of that high commanding
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:62733:38"/>Power, is far beyond all Robbery, Burglary, Rapine, or other Villa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny the World can invent.</p>
               <p>To Err wilfully, and out of a cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt deſign; is a greater fault, and more unpardonable, than to err through miſtake; but the hurt is the ſame to him that is injur'd by the wrong Decree; Therefore if we were ſure there would never be any ſuch Corruption any more, yet Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion ought to be made againſt mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtakes, ſince thoſe have been very frequent: whereof I ſhall give ſome inſtances, and for which you ſhall need to look no further back then to the Journals of the Lords Houſe in the laſt Seſſion of Parliament at <hi>Weſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minſter,</hi> where you may find that the 17th. of <hi>November</hi> 1680. a De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree in <hi>Chancery</hi> was Reverſed upon the Appeal of <hi>Crabb</hi> againſt <hi>Fenton,</hi> and the 22d. of the ſame Month a Decree in <hi>Chancery</hi> was Revers'd by the Lords upon the Appeal of <hi>Turner</hi> againſt <hi>Turner;</hi> and on the
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:62733:39"/>26th. of the ſame Month, another Decree in <hi>Chancery</hi> was Revers'd upon the Appeal of one <hi>Chute</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>Dacres,</hi> and many more Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peals were brought in that Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, which yet remain undeter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>min'd; and ſince the Lord-Keeper <hi>North</hi>'s having the Seal, he hath Revers'd ſeveral of the late Lord Chancellor <hi>Nottingham</hi>'s Decrees without any new matter ariſing ſince the Decree made, ſo that one of them muſt be miſtaken, but which of them, will not appear but by the judgment of divers others of as great Learning and Judgment as them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and ſo it is to be determin'd; for many may ſee more than one, and I conceave the King may give them Authority ſo to do, without putting the Kingdom to the Charge and Trouble of convening a Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, as by the enſuing part of this Treatiſe will appear.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="section">
               <pb n="69" facs="tcp:62733:39"/>
               <head>SECT. VI. <hi>That an Appeal to the</hi> King <hi>in the Intervals of</hi> Parliament, <hi>is an Ancient, Legal Remedy againſt miſtaken Decrees in</hi> Chancery, <hi>with the manner of Proceeding therein.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>IT becomes not a ſingle man to be too poſitive in his own Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, therefore I ſhall only at pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent ſay, that I am moſt extreamly miſtaken in my Calculations, if His Majeſty hath not ſufficient Power in the Intervals of Parliament, as the Law is at this day, being the 26th. of <hi>June</hi> 1683. to provide for his Subjects, and to Relieve them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt unjuſt Decrees in <hi>Chancery,</hi> if the matter be duely look'd into, notwithſtanding the Art and La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour that hath been uſed to conceal it; Therefore for maintaining of that
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:62733:40"/>point, I ſhall once more repeat a Sentence out of <hi>Bracton, <hi>Et defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dous generaiment a tout que nul ne eyt poer de amender nul faux Juge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment de nous Juſtices ſauve les Juſtices que ſuent nous et noſtre Court</hi>
                  </hi> que a ceo ſont per nous en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titles <hi>ou nous meſme on noſtre Councel cat ceo reſervouns nous eſpecialment a noſtre Jurisdiction;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Bracton <hi>fol.</hi> 3.</note> and <hi>Fleta</hi> ſpeaks to the ſame pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, <hi>Habet enim Rex curiam ſua &amp;c. habet etiam curiam ſuam &amp; Juſticiarios ſuos tam millites quam Clericos locum ſuum tenentes in</hi> Anglia <hi>coram quibus &amp; non alibi,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Fleta</hi> l. 2. fo. 66.</note> NISI CORAMSEMET IPSO ET CONCILIO SUO VEL AUDITORIBUS SPECIALIBUS, <hi>Falſa Judicia &amp; Errores Juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciariorum Revertuntur &amp; corri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guntur:</hi> Whence it is manifeſt that when thoſe Authors wrote the Power of Reverſing Erroneous (or <hi>Falſa</hi>) unjuſt Judgments of all other
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:62733:40"/>Courts was in the Juſtices that fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed the King, and his Court be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thereunto Authoriz'd by the King; but if they had Err'd, the Error was to be Rectified by his Councel or ſpecial Auditors, ſuch as the King ſhould think fit, or by the King himſelf, the ſupreme Juriſdicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and <hi>Dernier</hi> reſort being in the King himſelf, or where he pleaſed to place it, <hi>Car ceo reſervonus nous eſpecialment a noſtre Juriſdiction.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And this is alſo declar'd to be ſo by Act of Parliament in the 52 of <hi>H.</hi> 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 10. which ordains, <hi>That noue from thenceforth, except out Lord the King ſhall hold in his Court any plea of falſe Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments given in the Court of his Cennants, for ſuch Plea eſpecially belongeth to the Crown and Dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity of our Lord the King.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Though the Supream Juriſdiction were in the King to uſe as he ſaw beſt, it is but rational that if the Parliament were ſitting at ſuch time
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:62733:41"/>as any Complaints were made to him of any Erroneous Judgment or Decree, that he ſhould refer the Examination and final Determina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the matter to the Houſe of Lords, who without any manner of doubt, are, and always were, the fitteſt Referrees the King could re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer any matter to be determin'd, they being the chief Aſſembly of the Honour, Integrity, Wiſdom and Juſtice of the Nation, and therefore it is but reaſonable the King ſhould take the meaſures of his final Deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination from their Advice, or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer it to them to determine, which is all one, Better or Abler Advi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors being not to be found; but it is as true they had no power of Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing by their own innate Authority, but by a delegated Authority from the Kings, as plainly appears by what is ſaid before, and alſo by the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament Roll of the 4 of <hi>Ed.</hi> 3. which is recited in <hi>Cotton</hi>'s Records, <hi>In haec Verba,</hi> viz. <hi>The Treaſons, Felonies, and
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:62733:41"/>other miſdemeanors of</hi> Roger Morti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer <hi>are particularly repeated, a great part of which</hi> Roll <hi>cannot be read, for that the</hi> Roll is <hi>mouldred; but in the end it appears, that the King charg'd the Lords and Peers, who as Judges of the Realm by the Kings Aſſent, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judged that the ſaid</hi> Roger <hi>ſhould be Drawn and Hang'd:</hi> Whereby it appears it is the Kings Charge to the Lords, and the Kings Aſſent that gives them Juriſdiction and Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority: And ſo it follows of neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry conſequence, that though they are the fitteſt for the King to Authorize to determine the miſtakes and Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors of his Chancellors and other Judges; yet, if when they are not Aſſembled in a Parliamentary way, there is no reaſon nor authority a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt it, nor inconveniency by it, for the King to Authorize a convenient number of the Lords of the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and Judges that are near him to take courſe with Erroneous De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crees in the mean time until the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:62733:42"/>ſits; And therefore it was that it was provided by Act of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament the 31ſt. of <hi>Ed.</hi> 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 12. <hi>That the Lord</hi> Chancellor <hi>and</hi> Treaſurer <hi>ſhould have Power upon Complaint to take the Juſtices, and ſuch other ſage perſons as they thought fit, to their Aſſiſtance, and to Examine the Judgments of the</hi> Exchequer <hi>Court. And if any Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror be found, they may corted the Rolls, and after ſend them into the</hi> Exchequer <hi>to make I thereof Execution:</hi> Which thing I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the King might have done of himſelf without Act of Parliament; and I conceive the Act made it a ſtanding Rule to prevent often trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling the King upon every particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar occaſion; and though there be no proviſion by that Act for any further Examination of the Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Chancellor and Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurer in that Caſe; yet it is not ſo final, but the King may upon Peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to him, order a Writ of Error
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:62733:42"/>returnable in the Houſe of Lords Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembled in Parliament for a further and more due Examination of the matter if either Party thinks himſelf agrieved thereby, and from that time forward, <hi>ziz.</hi> the 31 of <hi>Ed.</hi> 3. there was no ſtanding Order made by Act of Parliament, as to the Errors of the Court of <hi>Kings-Bench,</hi> for by that Name I ſhall now call the Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſors of the Judges that followed the King mentioned in the aforeſaid Authors, but it ſtood at the Kings meer pleaſure,
<note place="margin">27 <hi>El.</hi> 8.</note> as for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly, until the 27 of Queen <hi>Elizabeth:</hi> Yet our latter Kings before that Statute, for the moſt part uſed to refer the Examina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and Correction of ſuch Errors only to their Houſe of Lords in Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, inſomuch that for want of oftener referring it to their Councel, or to <hi>Specialibus Auditoribus,</hi> Special Commiſſioners, as <hi>Fleta</hi> affirms the King could do, as is mention'd in the beginning of this Section; it grew to
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:62733:43"/>be an Opinion, that Errors of the Court of <hi>Kings Bench</hi> could be recti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied no where but in Parliament, as appears by the Preamble of that Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute of the 27 of <hi>Eliz.</hi> Therefore and as the Preamble of that Statute men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, <hi>Becauſe the Court of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſament was not in thoſe days ſo often held as in ancient time; and becauſe in reſpect of the great Affairs of the Realm, ſuch Errone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Judgments,</hi> (meaning thoſe of the <hi>Kings Bench) could not be well conſider'd and determin'd in time of Parliament; whereby the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects of the Realm were greatly hindred and deſayed of Juſtice.</hi> It was therefore enacted, <hi>That the Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors of Judgments in the ſaid Court of</hi> Kings-Bench <hi>in certain Actions therein mention'd, ſhould be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amined and rectified in the</hi> Exche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quer-Chamber <hi>by ſuch perſons as in the ſaid Act is mentioned; and after the Judgment is affirmed or tederſed, the Record, and all things
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:62733:43"/>concerning the ſame, ſhall be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moved and brought back into the Court of</hi> Kings-Bench, <hi>that ſuch further proceedings may be there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon, as well for execution as o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther wiſe, as ſhall appertain.</hi> And thereby it is reſerv'd, <hi>That the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties ſhall not be finally concluded by ſuch Reverſal or Affirmation, but that they may ſue in the high Court of Parliament for a further and more due examination of the ſaid Judgment, in ſuch ſort as was thentofore uſed upon erroneous Judgments:</hi> And the manner then<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tofore was, that before any Writ of Error could be brought to examine and correct Errors in Parliament, a Petition was to be preferred to the King for allowance thereof, and it was to be allowed by the King be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore any ſuch Writ of Error could be made, as appears by the Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rities in the margin;
<note place="margin">1 <hi>H.</hi> 7. fo. 19, 20. <hi>Dy.</hi> fo. 375.</note> which makes it moſt plain <hi>where</hi> &amp; in <hi>whom</hi>
                  <pb n="78" facs="tcp:62733:44"/>the Supreme Judicative Power lay. And Judge <hi>Jenkins</hi> ſays,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Jenk.</hi> Lex terrae, fo. 55.</note> 
                  <hi>The reaſon of the Law, and the King's al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowance of a Writ of Error, returnable in the Houſe of Lords, is, for that the Judges of the Land, all of them being of the Kings Councel, and the twelve Maſters in Chancery, aſſiſt in the Lords Houſe, by whoſe advice erroneous Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments are redreſt:</hi> So that it appears plainly, their Judicative Power in that particular is not originally and fundamentally in themſelves, but derived from the King, by his allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance thereof, who is <hi>fons &amp; origo Justitiae;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Bract.</hi> lib. 2. cap. 4.</note> and, ſays <hi>Bra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cton, est enim Coronae Regis facere Justitiam &amp; Judicium &amp; tenere pacem ſine qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus Corona conſistere non poteſt nec tenere, hujuſmodi autem jura ſive Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſdictiones ad perſonas ſive tenementa transferri non poterunt nec per priva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta perſona poſſideri nec uſus nec exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutio Juris, niſi hoc datum fuerit ei
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:62733:44"/>de ſuper ſicut Juriſdictio delegata non delegari poterit quin Ordinaria rema<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neat cum ipſo Rege.</hi> And I find by the Journal of the Lords Houſe, that the 10th. of <hi>December</hi> 1621. a Report was made by a Committee appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to ſearch for Precedents touching Appeals to the Lords from Decrees in Chancery,
<note place="margin">In the Stat. 37 <hi>E.</hi> 3.18. by <hi>Gr. Councel</hi> is meant the <hi>Privy-Council</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>That anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently all Petitions of that nature were directed to the K. and his great Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cel.</hi> From whence I gather, it is but a late practice, both to leave the King quite out of ſuch Petitions, and to neglect praying his allowance, that the Lords may examine Errors of Judgements and Decrees; And perhaps it may prove of ill con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence hereafter, if not timely conſidered and rectified: the Supre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macy of Juriſdiction being the Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme part of Government,
<note place="margin">Mir. 232.</note> &amp; the King's chiefeſt Dignity.</p>
               <p>By the foreſaid Statutes of <hi>E.</hi> 3. and <hi>El.</hi> and ſome others ſince made,
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:62733:45"/>there is ſufficient proviſions againſt erroneous Judgments in all Courts at Law in the intervals of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, by Writs of Error, which are in nature of Appeals; which courſe (I conceive) the King might have taken, if no ſuch Act had been made: But againſt the Judgments and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crees of the Courts of Equity in <hi>Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cery, Exchequer Chamber</hi> and <hi>Counties Palatine, &amp;c.</hi> there is no proviſion at all by any Parliamentary Act; that matter ſtanding as it did by the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-Law, no Parliament having in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termeddled with it; which if they had, they had the ſame reaſon, or more, to deſire the King to conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute a Court of Appeal from theſe Courts of Equity, as from other Courts. And it is a great Argument with me, (if there were no other) that it was conceived by the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, that there is a Power in the King alone out of Parliament-time to rectiſie the Errors of the Decrees of all Courts of Equity, elſe the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:62733:45"/>I preſume, would have taken care to have provided againſt thoſe, as well as againſt the Errors of the Court of <hi>Kings-Bench;</hi> which pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion was made, becauſe they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived thoſe Errors not to be redreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed but in Parliament; and the ſame reaſon that induced the Parliament to conſtitute Courts to redreſs the Errors of the <hi>Kings-Bench</hi> and <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chequer, viz.</hi> the unfrequency of Parli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liaments, and their being otherwiſe employ'd when they fit, may induce the King to appoint Referrees to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctifie Chancery-Decrees.</p>
               <p>For the further clearing of this matter, it ſeems in Queen <hi>Eliza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beths</hi> time there was the like doubt made as now, <hi>Whether the Queen might relieve againſt the mistakes of the</hi> Chancellor <hi>or</hi> Keeper, <hi>in making his Decrees?</hi> And the Queen took the right way to be inform'd, ſhe referr'd it to the Judges, to certifie to her their Opinion touching that matter: For it appears,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rolls</hi> Re. 1 p. 331.</note> by the Authority in the
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:62733:46"/>Margin, that it was certified by all the Judges of <hi>England,</hi> in the Cauſe between the Counteſs of <hi>Southamp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton</hi> and the Earl of <hi>Worceſter</hi> in <hi>Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cery,</hi> that the Queen, upon Petition, might refer the matter to the Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es (but not to others) to examine and reverſe the Decree, if there ſhould be cauſe; and that the then Lord Chancellor agreed to that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution. And foraſmuch as it is men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned in that Report, that the refer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence ought to be to the Judges, and not to others: it is to be underſtood, that it was a point in Law was then in diſpute, and in ſuch Caſes there muſt be ſome Judges amongſt them; for, <hi>in arte ſua cui<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> credendum eſt;</hi> and therefore Judges (whoſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion the ſtudy of the Law is) are preſum'd to be beſt conuſant of any what the Law is; and the Law is not to be unregarded in judging ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to Equity, but both Law and Conſcience are to be ſo inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mix'd, as to produce a juſt Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment;
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:62733:46"/>a skill of great curiouſity, and ought therefore not to be final, but in the reſolution of ſeveral men of great knowledge and integrity, ſince the leaſt byaſs of affection or diſguſt to one ſide or other, may lead any ſingle man a great way out of the way.</p>
               <p>I preſume this may be the mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of that Report, becauſe I find in the Year-book of the 27th. of <hi>H.</hi> 8. ſo. 15, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> That the Kings Secreta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry and Mr. <hi>Fitz-Herbert</hi> were join'd with the Chancellor to review a De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree between the Prior of St. <hi>Johns</hi> and one <hi>Dockeray,</hi> where the Secre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary gave rules in the Cauſe as well as the Chancellor.</p>
               <p>The Houſe of Lords themſelves al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways take the advice of the Judges; and to leave matters of Equity wholly to the Chancellor alone in the intervals of Parliament, is to give him a greater power than the Lords take to themſelves in Parliament; which, I humbly conceive, ought not to be.</p>
               <pb n="84" facs="tcp:62733:47"/>
               <p>Beſides this reſolution of all the Judges, aſſented to by the then Lord Chancellor, it was afterwards agreed to by the Houſe of Lords themſelves, That it was proper for the King to give authority to exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine and correct Decrees in Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cery, as appears by their own Order, which is as followeth, <hi>viz.</hi>
               </p>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="petition">
                  <body>
                     <opener>
                        <date>
                           <hi>Die</hi> Veneris <hi>viceſimo octavo die</hi> Maii, 1624.</date>
                     </opener>
                     <p>
                        <hi>THe Petition of</hi> Will. Matthews <hi>of</hi> Landaſt <hi>was read, and the Anſwer thereunto conceiv'd by the Lords Committees for Petitions (after Councel heard on both ſides many ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral days) was reported to the Houſe by the Lord</hi> Houghton, <hi>and read,</hi> in haec verba, <hi>viz.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>The Lords Committees upon the examination of the whole Cauſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween <hi>William</hi> and <hi>George Matthews,</hi> find <hi>William Matthews</hi> principal Debt to be Five thouſand two hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred and ſixty pounds, which they
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:62733:47"/>hold fit to be paid by the ſaid <hi>George Matthews</hi> thus:
<list>
                           <item>
                              <hi>
                                 <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon St.</hi> Andrews <hi>day next, One thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand ſix hundred twenty four,</hi> 2000 l.</item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>
                                 <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon St.</hi> Andrews <hi>day, One thouſand ſix hundred twenty five,</hi> 2000 l.</item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>
                                 <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon St.</hi> Andrews <hi>day, One thouſand ſix hundred twenty ſix,</hi> 1260 l.</item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>The whole ſum,</hi> 5260 l.</item>
                        </list>
                     </p>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <p>And that for ſecurity for the pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of this Debt according to every ſeveral day and payment here ſet down, the whole Land to ſtand bound; and that this be the better performed, the Lords Committees think fit the execution hereof be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commended to the Court of <hi>Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cery.</hi>
               </p>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="petition">
                  <body>
                     <opener>
                        <date>Die <hi>Veneris</hi> viceſimo octavo die <hi>Maii, 1624.</hi> poſt meridiem.</date>
                        <signed>
                           <hi>George Matthews</hi> exhibited his Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tition, <hi>in haec verba,</hi> viz.</signed>
                        <pb n="86" facs="tcp:62733:48"/>
                        <salute>To the Right Honourable the Lords Spiritual and Temporal, in the higher Houſe of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment aſſembled. The humble Petition of <hi>George Matthews,</hi> Eſq;</salute>
                     </opener>
                     <p>Humbly ſheweth your Lordſhips,</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>THat your Petitioners Decree now queſtion'd, hath been ſeveral times ſubmitted unto by</hi> William Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thews, <hi>never question'd during the life of the Petitioners Father; and His Majesty, upon information by Petition on both ſides, declared,</hi> That he ſaw no Cauſe for queſtioning thereof; <hi>and it was thereupon ordered,</hi> That to hear a Cauſe after ſubmiſſion, (no Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption appearing) would be a dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous Precedent. <hi>In conſideration whereof, and for that the Decree ſtands question'd only by Petition, nor was your now Petitioner ever party to any
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:62733:48"/>Suit, nor is there any Bill depending in Court; he being informed by Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cel, that it hath been the courſe of this Honourable Houſe to reverſe Decrees but by Bill legally exhibited, eſpecially where no corruption is prov'd:</hi>
                        <q>He therefore moſt humbly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeecheth, That he may have the liberty of a Subject, and that he may not be concluded, and a Decree ſubmitted unto over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thrown, and the ſmall remainder of his ancient Inheritance taken from him, by Order of this Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable Houſe, only upon a Petition. He moſt humbly ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mits himſelf herein to your Lordſhips, and will ever pray for your Honourable preſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</q>
                     </p>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <p>This Petition being read and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered of, theſe Lords, (<hi>viz.</hi>) the Earl of <hi>Montgomery,</hi> the Lord Biſhop of <hi>Durham,</hi> the Lord <hi>Say and Seal,</hi> and the Lord <hi>Denny,</hi> were appointed
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:62733:49"/>by the Houſe to ſet down an Order in this Cauſe between <hi>William</hi> and <hi>George Matthews.</hi>
               </p>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="order">
                  <body>
                     <opener>
                        <date>
                           <hi>Die</hi> Sabbati, <hi>viceſimo nono die</hi> Maii, 1624.</date> 
                        <hi>THe Lords Committees appointed yesterday in the afternoon to ſet down an Order in the Cauſe between</hi> William <hi>and</hi> George Matthews, <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported the ſame to the Houſe</hi> in haec verba, <hi>viz.</hi>
                     </opener>
                     <p>THe Lords of Parliament do order, That the Cauſe depending between <hi>Will. Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thews</hi> and <hi>George Matthews</hi> ſhall be reviewed in <hi>Chancery</hi> by the Lord Keeper, aſſiſted by ſuch of the Lords of Parliament as ſhall be nominated by the Houſe, and by any two of the Judges whom the Lord Keeper ſhall name;
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:62733:49"/>for which end the Lord Keeper is to be an humble Suitor unto his Majeſty from the Houſe, for a Commiſſion unto himſelf and the Lords that ſhall be named by the Houſe, for the ſaid Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>view and final Determination of the Cauſe, as to them ſhall appear Juſt and Equal: And this the Lords deſire may be done with all convenient ſpeed.</p>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <p>
                  <hi>The which Order being read, the Houſe approved thereof, and theſe Lords were named by the Houſe to be joyn'd in the ſaid Commiſſion with the Lord Keeper,</hi> viz. <hi>the Lord Chamberlain, the Earl of</hi> Montgomery, <hi>the Earl of</hi> Bridgwater, <hi>the Lord Biſhop of</hi> Dur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham, <hi>the Lord Biſhop of</hi> Rocheſter, <hi>the Lord</hi> Denny, <hi>and the Lord</hi> Houghton; <hi>and the Houſe ordered the ſame Cauſe to be heard and deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:62733:50"/>accordingly in the beginning of the next</hi> Michaelmas Term.</p>
               <p>This agrees <hi>verbatim</hi> with the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cords of the Lords Houſe; and pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuant thereunto, the matter was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>view'd by theſe Commiſſioners and a Decree by them made in reverſal of the Chancery-Decree, as appears by the Regiſters Book of Orders in <hi>Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cery,</hi> of <hi>Michaelmus</hi> and <hi>Hillary Term</hi> in the 22d. year of King <hi>James.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Sir <hi>Edward Cooke,</hi> in his Juriſdicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Courts,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Anderſon</hi> 2 part 163. to the ſame effect.</note> Title <hi>Chancery,</hi> with greatap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probation reports ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Caſes of Decrees in Chancery referred to the Judges by Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> to be examined and amended; and it is to be no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, that his authority in that Caſe was ſevenfold; for when he wrote that Book, he was very much incens'd againſt the King for being put out of his Chief Juſticeſhip, and ſet him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf as much as he could againſt the
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:62733:50"/>Prerogative, as appears by the whole current of that Book; ſo that had there been any colour of denying the Queen this Power, he had never cited thoſe Caſes without Objecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</p>
               <p>It was not only practiced by Qu. <hi>Elizabeth</hi> and King <hi>James,</hi> but alſo by King <hi>Charles</hi> the firſt, as appears by an Order which I find in the ſaid Regiſters Office in the Book of Entry of Orders there of the 22d. of <hi>No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vember,</hi> in the 7th. year of King <hi>Charles</hi> the firſt, between one <hi>Sher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bourn,</hi> the Executor of one <hi>Munford,</hi> the Executor of one <hi>Challener,</hi> Plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiff, and one <hi>Townley</hi> and <hi>Forreſt</hi> Defendants; which begins thus:</p>
               <q>
                  <p>
                     <hi>THe matter upon his Majesties reference to the Right Honoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble the Lord Keeper, upon the humble Petition of the ſaid</hi> Townley, <hi>coming this day to be heard in the preſence of Councel learned on both ſides, before his Lordſhip, being aſſiſted by Mr. Juſtice</hi>
                     <pb n="92" facs="tcp:62733:51"/>Hutton, <hi>Mr. Juſtice</hi> Jones, <hi>Mr. Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stice</hi> Whitlock, <hi>and Mr. Juſtice</hi> Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vey, <hi>the Question appear'd to be,</hi> Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, or how far, the ſaid <hi>Townley</hi> ought to be bound by the Decree made on the behalf of the ſaid <hi>Mun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford</hi> for the ſum of 17000 <hi>l.</hi> againſt the Defendant <hi>Townley,</hi> in Caſe the Defendant <hi>Thomas Forrest</hi> ſhould not pay the ſame? <hi>And upon the hearing, a Bill of Review was ordered to be brought by</hi> Townley, <hi>either upon mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter not inſiſted on at the first hearing, or new matter, and according to the courſe of the Court, the ſaid</hi> Town<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ley <hi>was ordered to give ſecurity, and in the mean time the execution of the ſaid Decree, and all proceedings there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon, as against the ſaid</hi> Townley, <hi>was reſpited and ſuſpended; and whereas by the first Decree</hi> Town<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ley <hi>was decreed to pay as well what his Co-Truſtee</hi> Forreſt <hi>had received of the Profits of the Eſtate of</hi> Challener, <hi>as what he had received himſelf: <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>p<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the hearing upon the ſaid Bill of
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:62733:51"/>Review, the first Decree was revers'd, and</hi> Townley <hi>decreed to anſwer only ſo much as he himſelf had received, which appear'd by the proofs to be but three half years Rent, and it was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred to a Master in Chancery to au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit the account touching the three half-years Rent, and the Recognizance gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven by</hi> Townley <hi>to perform the Order of the Court, was diſcharged.</hi>
                  </p>
               </q>
               <p>In the ſame Regiſters Office I find another Entry of an Order of <hi>June</hi> 1. in the 12th. year of King <hi>Charles</hi> the firſt, between one <hi>Pennington</hi> and others Plaintiffs, and one <hi>Holmes</hi> Defendant, in theſe words:</p>
               <q>
                  <p>
                     <hi>WHereas, upon Petition exhibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to the Kings most Excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Majesty by the Defendant, ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing ſome injustice and wrong to have been done unto him by a Decree made in this Court between the foreſaid par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, his Majesty was moſt graciouſly pleaſed to refer the matter to the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:62733:52"/>of the</hi> Rolls, <hi>to call to his aſſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance one of the Judges of the</hi> Bench, <hi>and to hear what could be alledged a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst the ſaid Decree: And this day being appointed for the hearing of the matter, the Master of the</hi> Rolls <hi>calling to him Mr. Justice</hi> Crooke, <hi>and having heard the parties and their Councel on both ſides, and what could be alledged against the ſaid Decree, why the ſame ſhould not be put in exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution, ſaw no cauſe to recede from, or alter the ſame.</hi>
                  </p>
               </q>
               <p>Now, after the Opinion of all the Judges of <hi>England,</hi> aſſented to by the then Lord Chancellor for the le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gality of this ſort of proceeding, and the approhation of the Houſe of Lords, and their direction for humble Suit to be made to the King for a Commiſſion from Him to proceed accordingly; and after ſo continu'd a ſeries of practice for the Reign of Three of the beſt Princes that ever ſway'd a Scepter, without the leaſt
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:62733:52"/>Objection then made againſt it by any that I ever read or heard of: I ſay, after all this, ſure one would think there could be no room for any colour of illegality in that ſort of Proceeding.</p>
               <p>But it is objected, That the Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer and Right of this ſort of procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding is ſince taken away by the Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute of 16 <hi>Car.</hi> 1. cap. 10. But I hold, that Statute doth not do it in the leaſt, nor doth it carry in it the leaſt colour or look that way; though, indeed, it doth take away ſomewhat too much (as I conceive) of the King's Power, but not this of <hi>refer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the examination and correcting of erroneous and unjuſt Decrees in Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cery to fit perſons for that purpoſe.</hi> I am ſure 'tis not prohibited by that Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute by any particular words, nor are there any general words therein contain'd, that according to the rules of Law, and conſtruction of other Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes, can be conſtrued to extend to the taking away of that courſe of
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:62733:53"/>proceeding. For the clearing of which point, it is requiſite that the Statute ſhould be taken ſtrictly into conſideration; the prohibiting part whereof is as followeth:</p>
               <q>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Be it Ordaiued and Enacted by the Authority of this preſent Parli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ament, That the ſaid Court, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly called the</hi> Star-Chamber, <hi>and all Juriſdiction, Power and Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity belonging to or exerciſed in the ſame Court, or by any Judges, Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers and Miniſters thereof, be from the firſt day of</hi> Auguſt 1641. <hi>clearly and abſolutely diſſolved, ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken away and determined; and that from the ſaid firſt day of</hi> Auguſt, <hi>nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the Lord Chancellor, nor the Kéeper of the Great Seal of</hi> England, <hi>the Lord Creaſurer of</hi> England, <hi>the Kéeper of the Kings Privy-Seal, or Preſident of the Councel, nor any Biſhop, Temporal Lord, Privy-Councellor, Judge or Juſtice what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever, ſhall have any Power or Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority to hear, examine or deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine any matter or thing whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, in the ſaid Court commonly cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:62733:53"/>the</hi> Star-Chamber, <hi>or to make, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce, or deliver any Judgment, Sentence, Order or Decree, or do any Judicial or Miniſterial act in the ſaid Court: and all and every Article, Clauſe and Sentence in them and every of them, by which any Juriſdiction, Power or Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity is given, limited, and appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted unto the ſaid Court commonly called the</hi> Star-Chamber, <hi>or unto all or any the Judges, Officers, or Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters thereof, or for any proccedings to be had or made in the ſaid Court, or for any matter or thing to be drawn into queſtion, examined or determined there, ſhall, for ſo much as concerneth the ſaid Court of</hi> Star-Chamber, <hi>and the Power and Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity thereby given unto it, be from the ſaid firſt day of</hi> Auguſt <hi>repealed, and abſolutely revoked and made void.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>And be it likewiſe Enaded, That the like Juriſdiction now uſed and exerciſed in the Court before the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſident and Councel in the Marches of</hi> Wales, <hi>and alſo before the Preſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent and Councel eſtabliſhed in the</hi> Northern-parts, <hi>and alſo in the Court
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:62733:54"/>commonly called</hi> the Court of the Dutchy of Lancaſter, <hi>before the Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellor, and Councel of that Court; and alſo in the Court of</hi> Exchequer <hi>of the County-Palatine of</hi> Cheſter, <hi>held before the Chamberlain and Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cel of that Court, the like Juriſdicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on being exerciſed there, ſhall from the firſt day of</hi> Auguſt 1641. <hi>he alſo repealed and abſolutely revoked and made void, any Law, Preſcription, Cuſtom, or Uſage,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>to the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry thereof in any wiſe notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding; and that from thenceforth no Court, Councel, or place of Judica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture ſhall be erected, ordained, conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuted, or appointed, within the Realm of</hi> England <hi>or Dominion of</hi> Wales, <hi>which ſhall have, uſe, or exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe the ſame or the like Juriſdiction as is or hath haen uſed, practiced or exerciſed in the ſaid Court of</hi> Star-Chamber.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Be it likewiſe Declared and En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acted by the Authority of this preſent Parliament, That neither His Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty nor His Privy-Councel have or ought to have any Juriſdiction, Power and Authority, by Engliſh Bill, Petition, Article, Libel, or
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:62733:54"/>any other arbitrary way whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, to examine or draw into queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, determine or diſpoſe of the Lands, Tenements, Dereditaments, Goods or Chattels of any of the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects of this Realm; but that the ſame ought to be tryed and deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined in the ordinary Courts of Juſtice, and by the ordinary courſe of Law.</hi>
                  </p>
               </q>
               <p>Theſe are all the prohibitory words of that Statute. I will not ſay any thing of the reaſonableneſs or un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reaſonableneſs of it, but that it was made in 41. But taking it as it is, I think it deſerves no further conſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction to diſable the King from per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forming his Oath, that is, <hi>to ſee that Juſtice ſhould be done to his Subjects,</hi> than the very expreſs words will bear; and for the right underſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of it, it is to be conſidered in all the parts thereof, without relying on any one ſingle Clauſe alone, and thereby it will appear how far the whole may be conſtrued to take
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:62733:55"/>away any Power that was before in the King.</p>
               <p>It takes away the <hi>Star-Chamber</hi> and the Power thereof, and prohi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bits the erecting of any Court of the like Juriſdiction, by expreſs terms; but by ſo doing it meddles not with this Power of the Kings to refer the examination of an unjuſt Decree made in Chancery by One man, to Three or Four, or more men, fit for the purpoſe, neither in terms nor in conſtruction: And it is a great ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument that it was never intended to be taken away by that Act, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is not taken away by expreſs words; for if it had been intended to have been taken away, it might have been expreſs'd by particular words, it being no new invention ſince the making of that Act, but a courſe long practis'd before that Act was made, as appears by what is aforeſaid, and that without the leaſt contradiction, but on the contrary, with the greateſt approbation that
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:62733:55"/>could be, <hi>viz</hi> the approbation and direction of the Lords Houſe in Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament at one time, and of all the Judges of <hi>England</hi> at another time, as is aforeſaid, and of all the great Writers of the Law of thoſe times; ſo that there was then no apparent reaſon for taking it away.</p>
               <p>The next part of the Statute, and that which ſeems moſt to oppoſe me, is, <q rend="inline">
                     <hi>That the King nor His Privy-Councel have, or ought to have, any Juriſdiction, Power or Authority; by</hi> Engliſh <hi>Bill, Petition, Article, Libel, or any other arbitrary way, to examine, draw into question, determine, or diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe of the Lands, Tenements,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>but that the ſame ought to be tryed and determined in the ordinary Courts of Juſtice, and by the ordinary courſe of Law.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>For the underſtanding of this, it is to be remembred, the King, for the execution of the Law, had two ſorts of Powers in Him by the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-Law; He had Power and Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:62733:56"/>thority in Perſon to hear,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ordinaria Juriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictio pertinet ad Regem,</hi> Bract. fol. 108, 412. <hi>Ordinaris Juriſ. dictio remanet cumipſo Rege,</hi> Bract. fol. 55.</note> determine, and diſpoſe of the Eſtates of his Subjects, upon Controverſie ariſing between them, and complain'd of to him, and this is properly called <hi>Juriſdicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Deſignatio Justi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciariorum eſt à Rege Juriſdictio vere ordinaria à Lege,</hi> Co. 4 Inſt. fo. 74.</note> and he had alſo <hi>deſignatio Judiciorum,</hi> a power of nominating and appointing Judges under him to hear, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termine, and diſpoſe of the Eſtates of the Subjects, touching which any Controverſie did ariſe, and was brought before them to be decided, as appears in the beginning of this Treatiſe;
<note place="margin">Sect. 2. <hi>per tout.</hi>
                  </note> So that if he ſhould be excluded himſelf by this Statute from hearing and determining in perſon, yet there is not a word that excludes him from nominating Judges to hear and determine: Therefore, if he could nominate Referrees to rectifie a
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:62733:56"/>Chancery-Decree before the Statute, as moſt apparently he could, he may do ſo yet, there being not one word in the Statute that prohibits it. And whereas it prohibits all arbitrary ways whatſoever of diſpoſition of the Subjects Eſtates by the King or his Privy Councel, this courſe is not to promote Arbitraryneſs, but to prevent it; for it is more arbitrary to leave Cauſes to the final determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of one ſingle mans Judgment, than to refer it to the Judgment of five or ſix, it being not ſo eaſie to corrupt or deceive many as one, and that is the reaſon why a Tryal by Jury of Twelve is ſo much approv'd of, and applauded; for they being many,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Forteſcue</hi> fol. 75.</note> cannot all be eaſily corrupted.</p>
               <p>And as to that part of the Act that ſays, <hi>The fore-mentioned Eſtates ought to be tryed and determined in the ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary Courts of Justice, and by the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary courſe of Law:</hi> certainly none can ſay that have conſidered the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſes,
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:62733:57"/>but that referring the exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of Chancery-Decrees to a convenient number of ſage perſons, as is aforeſaid, may very well be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted a proceeding in Chancery according to the ordinary courſe of that Court, ſince the firſt practice of the Court was to determine not by the Chancellor alone, but by the conſent of divers others as is aforeſaid.
<note place="margin">Sect. 3.</note> And I conceive the Houſe of Lords terming it <hi>a reviewing of the Decree in Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cery,</hi> when they directed application to be made to the King for a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion, as is afore-mentioned, and all the Judges of <hi>England</hi> giving their Opinion for the legality of ſuch pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding, and the ſame conſented and agreed to by the then Lord Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellor, and the long continued pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice of it without any diſlike, (when there was occaſion) as I have made appear for ſeveral Princes Reigns, and until an unparallell'd Rebellion and Uſurpation, put that (as well as
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:62733:57"/>all things elſe) out of courſe; may intitle it to <hi>an ordinary courſe of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding,</hi> if any proceeding at all in Equity in Chancery can be ſo ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted; and the determining Cauſes there by the Chancellor himſelf, without any aſſiſtance or conſent of others, is more like an arbitrary and an extraordinary way, and new ſort of practice, than that.</p>
               <p>For further manifeſtation of this matter, and that a reference from the King to examine the injuſtice of a Chancery-Decree is a proceeding in Chancery, and no erecting of a new Court, and that as well when the Lord Chancellor or Lord Keeper is not one of the Referrees or Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſioners, as when he is, it appears by the proceeding upon the fore-men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned Reference by the King to the Maſter of the <hi>Rolls</hi> and a Judge of the <hi>Kings-Bench,</hi> to examine the injuſtice of the Decree between <hi>Pennington</hi> and <hi>Holmes</hi> afore-mentioned: That upon that reference, the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:62733:58"/>on the firſt Decree was ſtaid, and what was done thereupon is entred among the proceedings in <hi>Chancery,</hi> as an Act of that Court; And moreover,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Dúgd. Orig. Ju.</hi> fol. 32. That <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theldred</hi> appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the Office of Chancellor to be exercis'd by three <hi>Abbots</hi> by turns.</note> it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be deny'd but the King may commit the cuſtody of his Great Seal to ſeveral Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioners, as King <hi>James</hi> did upon the outing of the corrupt Lord <hi>Bacon;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">See the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment Roll of that time, and <hi>Dugd.</hi> Chronological Table of Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellors and Kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers.</note> and in ſuch caſes one of the Commiſſioners keeps the Seal, and is Preſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent amongſt the reſt, but they have all equal Authority in judging according to the purport of the Commiſſion,
<note n="*" place="margin">12 <hi>Maii</hi> 19 <hi>Jac.</hi> ordered in <hi>Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cery, inter Butler</hi> and <hi>Eliot,</hi> That the Decree made by the Lord <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>con</hi> ſhould not be ſigned by the Commiſſioners of the Great Seal, until notice to the other ſide, as by the Regiſters Book of Orders in Chancery of that day appears.</note> and do ſign De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crees; and if the King may make many Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es in Equity to hear
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:62733:58"/>all Cauſes generally, what is the reaſon he cannot appoint many Judges there in ſome few particular Cauſes, upon complaint of miſtake by his Chancellor or Keeper? ſince he that may do more can do leſs, and the King is not ty'd to have any cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain or limited number of Judges in his Courts; for there were in the <hi>Common-Pleas,</hi> in <hi>E.</hi> 4.'s time and before, ſometimes 6, 7, or 8, and King <hi>James</hi> had five Judges in the <hi>Kings-Bench,</hi> (whereof my Great-grand-father Sir <hi>David Williams</hi> was the fifth) and as many in the <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-pleas,</hi> about the beginning of his Reign, as may appear by <hi>Dugdale</hi>'s Chronological Table of Judges of that time: So that I cannot appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend any manner of prohibition, neither expreſs nor implied, in this Statute nor any other, againſt the Kings referring the examination and regulating unjuſt Decrees in Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cery to others, beſides the Chancel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lor or Keeper.</p>
               <pb n="108" facs="tcp:62733:59"/>
               <p>This Statute deſerves not to be extended beyond it ſelf, it being a penal Statute, which is never to be taken by Intendment, further then the very expreſs words of the Prohi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bition upon a ſtrict and bare con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction will bear, however the Statute it ſelf in the concluſion hath by expreſs words ſomewhat mended the matter from what is contain'd in the premiſſes; for in the end of the Act there is a Proviſoe which doth in effect reſtore the King to almoſt all his Ancient Juriſdiction, and puts all the ſeeming Cauſe of doubt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the matter of Referring the Examination of unjuſt Decrees in Courts of Equity quite out of doors, by confining the meaning and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of the Statute to the words of the Proviſoe therein contained, which Proviſoe is in theſe words, <q rend="inline">
                     <hi>Provided always, and be it En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acted, that this Act and the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Clauſes therein contain'd, wall be taken and Expounded to
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:62733:59"/>extend only to the Court of</hi> Star<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chamber, <hi>and the ſaid Court holden before the Preſident and Councel in the</hi> Marches of Wales, <hi>and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Preſident and Councel in the</hi> Northern <hi>parts, and alſo to the Court commonly call'd, the Court of the</hi> Dutchy of Lancaſter, <hi>holden before the Chancellor and Councel of that Court; and alſo in the</hi> Exchequer <hi>of the County Palatine of</hi> Cheſter, <hi>before the Chamberlain and Councel of that Court, and to all Courts of like Juriſdiction to be hereafter Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected, Drdain'd, conſtituted or ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed as aforeſaid, and to the Warrants and Directions of the Council-board, and to the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittments, Reſtraints and Impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonments of any perſon or perſons made, commanded and awarded by the Kings Majeſty, his Heirs and Succeſſors in their own Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, or by the Lords and others of the Privy-Council and every one
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:62733:60"/>of them.</hi>
                  </q> So that here's an Expla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation that no Court or Proceeding in any Court is to be taken away but the Court of <hi>Starchamber</hi> and the Juriſdiction thereof, and ſuch like Courts of like Juriſdiction; and this of the Kings referring the Exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination of unjuſt Decrees in <hi>Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cery</hi> to particular Commiſſioners and Referrees, was practis'd out of the <hi>Star-chamber,</hi> when that Court was at height, as may appear by the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cited Preſidents; ſo that it never was a part of the Juriſdiction or practice of that Court, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore declared by the ſaid Proviſoe not intended to be prohibited by the ſaid Act; and as to the King the Proviſoe ſays, He is to be reſtrai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned but from reſtraining and impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoning by his own perſonal com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, he may do every thing elſe that he could have done before; He may hear and determine in perſon, if he pleaſes, as he could have done before; and he may appoint all ſuch
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:62733:60"/>Judges or Referrees to all purpoſes, as he could have done before: But as to the Warrants of Impriſoning, if any cauſe for ſuch there ſhould be, he is to leave that to his Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters; and the King, if he thinks fit, upon complaint to him made of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſtice or other Error done by his Chancellor or Keeper, may order his Chancellor to order the parties concern'd to appear before the King in perſon, and the King himſelf may require his Chancellor or Keeper to be preſent, and his Majeſty may call others to his aſſiſtance, whom he may confide in for juſt and equitable advice, and may determine what to him ſeems meet in the Cauſe, upon conference with them, this being for <hi>advancement,</hi> not <hi>delay</hi> of Juſtice; and if the Chancellor or Keeper doth not uſe the coercive part of Impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonment, and other Proceſs of the Court of Chancery to compel Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to ſuch determination, I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive he doth not do his duty. I
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:62733:61"/>mention this, not that I think it's abſolutely neceſſary the King ſhould trouble himſelf to hear all matters in perſon, but I humbly conceive it not amiſs for his Majeſty ſometimes to uſe his Power in Chancery as well as at Councel-board, leſt for want of uſing his Power, he may be in danger of loſing it, and conſequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly his eſteem in the eyes of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, may be leſſen'd; whilſt every of his acting Judges (the Chancellor or Keeper eſpecially) command re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect from their Friends, and fear and trembling from their Enemies.</p>
               <p>I am ſure <hi>Solomon</hi>'s giving Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in the caſe of the Harlots gain'd him more eſteem, not only amongſt his own Subjects, but all the World over, than any one other act of Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment he did in all his Reign, and the Kings not being exactly skill'd in the Law, or the formal Rules there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, as a profeſs'd Lawyer ſhould be, ſhould not at all hinder his underta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king it ſometimes; for a man but
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:62733:61"/>of common ſenſe, having heard the Caſe put, the proofs made, and the Arguments of indifferent men, (not byaſs'd Advocates, or Councel on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly) may eaſily diſcern what Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is fit to be given in Equitable Cauſes; and the King hath almoſt infallible helps; He hath his Lords Spiritual and Temporal; He hath always at his call twelve Judges, men skill'd in the Laws, and ſworn law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully to counſel the King in all mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters: Theſe, or ſome of them, he may command to attend him at ſuch Hearings, and may command them to give their opinion of the matter, according to the nature of the Cauſe, and according to the beſt of their judgments; and the King at ſuch hearing may give, or cauſe to be giv'n a Sentence or Judgment according to the Opinion of the majority of them; and this courſe is the beſt, and was the old way of judging of Equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; and if us'd ſome times, would make Chancellors and Keepers more
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:62733:62"/>regard what they do: But if the King ſhould not be minded to med<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle in perſon with determining any Cauſes, his referring of the exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of Chancery-Decrees to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons fit and able, of judgment and knowledge to do it, may ſuffice, bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter then to leave it wholly to his Chancellors ſingle judgment; For, <hi>ſecurius expediuntur negotia comiſſa pluribus, &amp; plus vident oculi quam oculus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>There is at this day a ſtanding Commiſſion enroll'd in Chancery to all the Judges of <hi>Weſtminſter hall,</hi> the Maſter of the Rolls, and the other Maſters in Chancery, impowering any Three of them, (whereof the Maſter of the Rolls or one of the Judges to be one) in the abſence of the Lord Keeper to hear and deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine Cauſes, and that is not thought to be prohibited by any Statute: And if the King hath Authority and Power to appoint Commiſſioners for the Chancellor or Keepers eaſe, why
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:62733:62"/>cannot he alſo give po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer to Commiſſioners to rectifie his Decrees when he miſtakes?
<note place="margin">The Chancellor or Keeper of the Great Seal is but the King's De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puty during plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, 9 <hi>Rep.</hi> 99. and a Grant of that Office for life is void, <hi>Cooke</hi> 4 Inſt. fol. 87.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Upon the whole matter, I muſt conclude, I can apprehend no war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rantable objection can be made a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt this ſort of proceeding, or that any Statute doth, or intended to take it away: ſo that I ſhall take that point for granted, <hi>That it is ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry lawful for the King to appoint Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferrees or Commiſſioners to rectifie Chancery-Decrees, or Decrees of any other Court of Equity.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The next thing to be conſidered is, Whether any of the King's Privy-Councel may be Referrees or Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioners for that purpoſe, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding the ſaid Statute? For they are men of ſo great Honour, Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge and Integrity, and of ſuch Fortune and Eſtates, as to ſcorn Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bery, and therefore very fit to aſſiſt in
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:62733:63"/>this matter; and I hold <hi>They may;</hi> for the prohibition of the Act ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends to their not acting as being only and barely Privy-Councellors: It doth not ſay, <hi>Privy-Councellors ſhall not act by virtue of any other Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority.</hi> And this thing proves it ſelf plainly in the Caſe of the now Lord Keeper, and Lord Chief Juſtice of the <hi>Common-Pleas,</hi> who are both of the Privy-Councel, yet examine, draw into queſtion, determine and diſpoſe of the Lands, Tenements, Goods and Chattels of the Subjects, with a witneſs, by virtue of another Authority derived from the King; and if They may do it, why may not any other of the Privy Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cel act by a lawful Authority in thoſe matters, as well as They?</p>
               <p>The next thing conſiderable, is, if the Lord Chancellor or Keeper ought to command performance ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the courſe of the Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cery, of what ſuch Referrees do order by virtue of ſuch Reference,
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:62733:63"/>when he himſelf is not one of them; as well as when he is; and I hold <hi>he ought;</hi> Firſt, for what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever Order is made in the Houſe of Lords upon determining an Appeal from Chancery-Decrees, it is ſent to the Chancery, to compel Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence thereto; and in this reſpect, I conceive the Houſe of Lords are but the Kings Referrees, and do le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gally and truly derive their Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity from the King, as is prov'd by the due Proceedings upon Writs of Error, and the ancient form of Peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions againſt Chancery-Decrees be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore-mentioned: So that ſuch Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferrees do act by Authority derived from the King, as well as the Houſe of Lords in Parliament. And fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, the practice hath been for the Lord Chancellor or Keeper to purſue what is done by ſuch Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferrees; for what was reſolved by the Judges upon the References mentioned in Sir <hi>Edw. Cooke</hi> 4 Inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes, and certified by them to the
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:62733:64"/>Chancellor was comply'd with by him; and what was decreed by the major part of the Commiſſioners joyn'd with the Lord Keeper, in the Caſe of <hi>Matthews</hi> and <hi>Matthews</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore-remembred, was confirmed, and proſecuted by the Lord Keeper, as Lord Keeper, in and according to the courſe of Chancery; and ſo in the caſe of <hi>Sherburne</hi> and <hi>Townley;</hi> and had been ſo alſo in the caſe of <hi>Pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nington</hi> and <hi>Holmes</hi> before-mentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, if there had been any alteration of the Decree; for the confirmation of that Decree by virtue of the Kings referrence, is entred as an Act of that Court: ſo that I think that point is alſo pretty clear. And (I preſume) the enrolling or performing of a De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree, before Petition to the King, or before obtaining his Commiſſion or Order of referrence, (which are both as ſufficient one as the other, there being a ſufficient number of Prece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents of both ſorts) is no hindrance but that reſtitution may be awarded,
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:62733:64"/>if the Commiſſioners and Referrees make certificate to the Chancellor or Keeper that it ought to be ſo; for the enrollment of a Decree doth not make it more irrevocable then it was before the enrollment, but that notwithſtanding it may be alte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in the ſame Court; for it is not a Record, and in that reſpect not ſo high in the eye of the Law as a Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment according to the courſe of the Common-Law, which cannot be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers'd in the ſame Court; and this was ſo held in <hi>H.</hi> 8.'s time,
<note place="margin">27 <hi>H.</hi> 8. fol. 15.</note> in a Cauſe in Chancery before men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned in the 6th. Section, between the Prior of St. <hi>Johns</hi> and one <hi>Docke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ray;</hi> where upon a review in Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cery before the Lord Chancellor, the King's Secretery, and Mr. <hi>Fitz-Herbert,</hi> it was held and allowed, that a Decree there is but an Order made by the Court for the time; which upon good conſideration, and cauſe ſhewn, may well be altered,
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:62733:65"/>notwithſtanding all the arguments then made by the Councel for the firſt Decree, to prevent inſpecting into it, as that ſuch looking back ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to confuſion, and would make Cauſes endleſs, and the like: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto the Kings Secretary (ſitting then in equal authority with the Chancellor, as appears by the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port) made anſwer, and comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded the formal man that was againſt inſpecting the injuſtice of the Decree to forbear diſputing the Power of that Court; and ſuch was the pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice of the late Lord Chancellor <hi>Nottingham,</hi> who would often re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hear and re-hear again and again, upon Councels certify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it under their hands that there was good Cauſe,
<note place="margin">The Cauſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween <hi>Thacker</hi> &amp; <hi>Redman</hi> was ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral times heard by the Lord <hi>Not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tingham,</hi> and heard again by the Lord Keeper <hi>North</hi> on the 20th. of <hi>April,</hi> 35 <hi>Car.</hi> 2. after the Decree enroll'd; and upon that hearing, a Tryal at Law di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected, which muſt occaſion another hearing.</note> as they appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended,
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:62733:65"/>for ſuch rehearing his fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent ſaying, being, that the nimble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of a Clark in enrolling his De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree ſhould not hinder him from coming at Juſtice, and that he would leap over Hedge and Ditch to do it; and doubtleſs it is the true and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per power of that Court of Equity ſo to do: And though it doth of deſcretion entertain ſome Forms, yet it may, and ought upon occaſion to leave them, rather then tie up its own hands from doing Juſtice; for it hath <hi>Poteſtatem abſolutam ſecundum probata Judicare;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">9 <hi>E.</hi> 4. f. 15.</note> and if ever any Chancellor did amiſs in that reſpect, it was in that he would leap luſtily for ſome, but would not hop over a ſtraw for others: I wiſh none in that great place be ever more guilty of the like partiality.</p>
               <p>It appears from what is before-mentioned, that the Court of Equity in Chancery is the King's high Court of conſcience for moderating the ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gor, and ſupplying the defects of the
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:62733:66"/>Common-Law, and he may order it, and limit the Juriſdiction thereof as to him ſeems moſt agreeable to Equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and Juſtice; a further inſtance whereof appears by an Enrollment of a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion now to be ſeen in Chancery,
<note place="margin">At the <hi>Rolls,</hi> 6 pars 14 <hi>Jac.</hi> nu. 25.</note> beginning thus:</p>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="statute">
                  <body>
                     <opener>
                        <signed>JAMES <hi>by the Grace of God,</hi> &amp;c.</signed>
                     </opener>
                     <argument>
                        <p>wherein it is mentioned, <hi>That the Attorney-General and the reſt of the Kings Councel learned in the Law had been commanded to conſider and certi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie to the King if the Chancery might relieve according to Equity after a Judgment at Law;</hi> and therein is mentioned the conſultation had by the Kings Councel thereupon, and their reaſons on the point, and the Roll ends thus:</p>
                     </argument>
                     <p>
                        <hi>We in Our Princely judgment having well weigh'd, &amp; with mature deliberation conſidered of the ſaid ſeveral Reports of Our learned Councel, and all the parts of them,</hi> &amp;c.
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:62733:66"/>
                        <hi>Do will and command. That Our Chancellor or Keeper of the Great Seal for the time being, ſhall not hereafter deſiſt to give to Our Subjects, upon their ſeveral complaints now and hereafter to be made, ſuch relief in Equity, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withstanding any former proceeding at the Common-Law againſt them, as ſhall ſtand with the true merits and Justice of their caſes,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>And for that it appertains to Our Princely care and Office only to be Judge over all Our Judges, and to diſcern and determine ſuch differences as at any time may or ſhall ariſe between Our ſeveral Courts touching their Juriſdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, and the ſame to ſet and to decide as We in Our Princely Wiſdom ſhall find to ſtand moſt with Our Honour, and the example of Our Royal Proge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitors in the beſt of times, and the general Weal and Good of Our People, for which We are to anſwer to God, who hath placed <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>s over them. Our will and pleaſure is, That Our whole Proceedings herein, by the Orders
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:62733:67"/>formerly ſet down, be enroll'd in Our Court of</hi> Chancery, <hi>there to remain of Record, for the better extinguiſhment of the like Queſtion that may ariſe in future times.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <closer>
                        <dateline>
                           <date>Decimo octavo Julii, Anno Regni Regis <hi>Jacobi</hi> quarto. decimo,</date>
                        </dateline>
                        <signed>per ipſum Regem.</signed>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <p>But after all I have ſaid, if there be any that have conſidered the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſes, and will ſtill deny the Kings Power, I muſt alſo ſay, That for determination of the matter, the opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of his Majeſties learned Judges is to be the Touch-ſtone; therefore, for a further inducement to enquire further of them touching this matter, which is my principal aim hereby, I ſhall in the next place give a hint of the inconveniences that do happen for want of this courſe of Procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="section">
               <pb n="125" facs="tcp:62733:67"/>
               <head>SECT. VII. <hi>The Inconveniencies that accrew for want of a conſtant Relief againſt Erreneous and Unjuſt Decrees in</hi> Chancery.</head>
               <p>TO apprehend the miſchiefs that may enſue for want of a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant and permanent practical Power to controll and rectify miſtaken De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crees in <hi>Chancery,</hi> it is a neceſſary to look back to the fourth <hi>Section</hi> for the Power of that Court, and how far it extends, which is there ſet down in ſome meaſure.</p>
               <p>It is alſo conſiderable, how ill ſome Chancellors have us'd this their ſo great unlimited Power, which ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears in the Lord <hi>Bacon</hi>'s Caſe, here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in alſo before re-cited in the fifth <hi>Section;</hi> for it is not Impoſſible but that ſome of his Succeſſors may do the like, which if but any one ſhould,
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:62733:68"/>it would be very hard for many a poor Creature to wait the Conven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of a Parliament, eſpecially if it ſhould happen that another uſurping part of a Parliament like that about 41. ſhould attempt to play the old Game again; ſo that in ſuch caſe, the King muſt perhaps either leave many of his Subjects utterly undefended a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the corrupt and vicious pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings of another <hi>Bacon,</hi> or endan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger his own ſafety, by letting them ſit; in which caſe, by the Rule of Self-pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation, the King ought to ſave him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf: But ſetting aſide this matter of corruption, as if no ſuch would ever hereafter be in the World, if we conſider humane frailty, and the real miſtakes every ſingle man may be ſubject to; eſpecially when beſet with the mercenary Arguments of three or four Hireling Advocates of a ſide, who think themſelves oblig'd, when opportunity ſerves, to mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtake for their Clients, according to the meaſure of the Fees they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive,
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:62733:68"/>as I have known ſome of them knowingly do; and ſometimes they prevaricate and omit what they ought to ſay, if either Feed on both ſides, or not high enough Feed of the ſide they are of; by means whereof a circumſpect Lord Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellor or Keeper may innocently be ſeduc'd to make an ill Decree, and by force thereof a poor man muſt either go to Priſon, or part with the beſt part of his Subſtance, ſo that by both ways, himſelf and Family are brought unjuſtly to want and miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry; and if he be a Trades-man, it is ods but he breaks one or two more, for Trades-men are like Nine-pins, one ſeldom falls alone; and if a Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament when it meets ſhould find leaſure from publick buſineſs to exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine the matter, and ſhould ſee cauſe to alter the Decree, and Award Reſtitution, the man that got the Money by means of the ill Decree, may have ſpent it all, gone beyond Sea, or dead, without Aſſets, or
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:62733:69"/>twenty ſuch Chances may happen, that the Money may never be got again by any Art or Induſtry what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever, which would be prevented if there were a place to Appeal, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore performance of the ill Decree; and moreover, it remains a doubtful caſe as to the many Decrees of the late Lord Chancellor <hi>Notingham</hi> Re vers'd by the now Lord Keeper <hi>North,</hi> which of the two Lords are in the right, he that made the Decrees, or he that Revers'd them, it being not fairly to be decided, but by the Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice and Opinion of a greater num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of as Wiſe and Judicious men as themſelves, and that is a fair and reaſonable way of determining it, for <hi>vis unita fortior;</hi> but the greateſt inconvenience of all, is that which concerns the Government; for while this opinion ſtands, That the King cannot hear the matter in Perſon, nor refer it to others, though to ſome of the ſelf ſame Lords that ſit in Parliament; but that the matter
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:62733:69"/>muſt wait their meeting in a Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentary way, it may make the people believe that the Supremacy of Juriſdiction is in the Houſe of Lords, and not in the King, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently leſſen him in their opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion; for People Love and Honour them moſt from whom they find moſt Relief againſt Injury; and how conſiſtent that is with Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chy, and how agreeable it is with our Oaths willingly to ſuffer, let any man Judge that hath Senſe and Loyalty. Since all the Courts of <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> have four Judges in each Court, men Learned in the Laws, of known and viſible Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grity, and all Sworn, <hi>To do equal right to all,
<note place="margin">18 E. 3.7. <hi>Oath of Juſt.</hi>
                     </note> and to take no Fee or Roabes of any man great or ſmall, but of the King himſelf, during their be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Judges;</hi> And who in their pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings are ty'd to Rules; and ſince Appeals by Writ of Error, by ſpecial Proviſion by Act of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:62733:70"/>may be at all times had againſt their Judgments; and ſince there are frequent Appeals from all Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſtical Courts, and from the Court of Admirality out of Parliament. It is a mighty miſtery to me, and the policy of it is not Intelligible, that any man ſhould labour to prop up this Opinion, that there ſhould be no Appeal but to Parliament from this Court of Equity in <hi>Chancery,</hi> where there is now but one Judge, and his Orders and Decrees controuling all the Judgments of other Courts, and he therein ty'd to no other Rule but his own Conſcience, be it good or bad: I think a Chancellor or Keeper for his own Juſtification, ſhould not be againſt the Kings Examining his Decrees, or Referring them to fit perſons to be Examin'd and Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected, which without peradventure is not only the beſt and ſureſt way for Adminiſtration of Juſtice in this Caſe, and ſo far from ſetting up an Arbitrary way, or an Extraordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:62733:70"/>Courſe, that it is but reſtoring the Court of Equity in <hi>Chancery</hi> to its Ancient and Primitive form of Judicature, the definitive Judging there by the Chancellor alone be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing but an Innovation upon the Original Inſtitution of that Court, as appears by what is aforeſaid, and to the end there may be no ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction in the way, I have enquir'd how far the King ought by Law to provide for his Injur'd Subjects, in caſe of Appeal to him from Errone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous or Unjuſt Decrees in <hi>Chancery</hi> by a Lord Chancellor or Keeper.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="section">
               <head>SECT. VIII: <hi>Whether the King ought</hi> exdebito Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticiae <hi>to hear in Perſon, or to grant References upon Complaint to him made againſt Erroneous and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>njuſt Decrees in</hi> Chancery.</head>
               <p>I Have as great Veneration for Kingly Government, and am as
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:62733:71"/>Firm and Faithful to it as any man can be; however I think it no pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption to affirm, that the King ought to do his Subjects right, by uſing the beſt means he may for ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtration of Juſtice amongſt them, <hi>pertinet ad Regem ad quamlibit inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riam compeſcendam competens re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medium adhibere.</hi> It is no diſhnour to him that he is oblig'd to it, for it is for that end he is ordain'd by God and obey'd by men, it is therein conſiſts the height of his Clory and the luſtre of his Majeſty, and ſays <hi>Fleta,
<note place="margin">Fleta <hi>fo.</hi> 17. <hi>par.</hi> 15.</note> Whereas it is ſo ordain'd that every man in proſecution of his right,</hi> Potius judicio quam viribus utatur, <hi>Should make uſe of the Law rather than force:</hi> The injur'd are to come to the King, and having ſhew'd him the wrong they have ſuffer'd, he ought to do ſpeedy Juſtice to his Petitioners; yet the King is not to be troubled, but when his Ordinary judges fall of their Duty: For, <hi>Nemo
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:62733:71"/>in lite Regem appellato niſi quando domi jus conſequi non poterit.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Orig. <hi>Jul. fo.</hi> 20.</note>
               </p>
               <p>A Complaint to the King by Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tition againſt the Error and Injuſtice of a <hi>Chancery</hi> Decree, is an Appeal to the King from his Chancellor, from the Inferior Judge to the Supe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rior, which is very natural; and a Petition to him for allowance of a Writ of Error, to the Houſe of Lords to inſpect and certifie a Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Court of <hi>Kings-Bench,</hi> or <hi>Exchequer Chamber;</hi> and an Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peal to the King from his Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Courts, and from the Court of Admirality, are all grounded upon the ſame natural Juſtice; and by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the Kings Supremacy of Juriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction, and that as well by force of the Common as Statute Law.</p>
               <p>Of Appeals in general, Sir <hi>Edw. Cooke</hi> cites the Opinion of a Learned Judge of the Admirality, and ſome others to this effect, <hi>For as much as an Appeal is a natural defence, it
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:62733:72"/>cannot be taken away by any Prince or Power;
<note place="margin">Cook<hi>'s</hi> 4 <hi>Iuſt. fo.</hi> 340.</note> but if the Appeal be juſt and law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, the Superior Judge ought of right and Equity to receive and admit the ſame, as he ought to do Juſtice to the Subject; and ſo if the Cauſe of the Appeal be juſt and Lawful, he ought to Reverſe and Revoke all mean Acts done after the Appeal brought in prejudice of the Appeallaent:</hi> But I need not much labour that point, for I can Experimentally ſay, that His Majeſty is very deſirous that His Subjects ſhould have the full and free benefit of the courſe of Juſtice, and if any ever fail of it, it ought not to be imputed to the King, but to his Council, whoſe advice is the Kings guide; and if they miſ-adviſe the King, and he follows their advice, he is excuſable; yet he is not bound always to follow their advice, if he be really ſatisfied in himſelf after hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring their reaſons, that it ought to be otherwiſe than they adviſe; for
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:62733:72"/>as he is plac'd by God above them, it is to be preſum'd God may ſupply him with a more diſcerning Spirit than they, and enable him to diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh between the beſt and worſt advice, having heard the reaſons of both: Yet they that knowingly ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſe the King ill, or neglect to adviſe him well, when occaſion requires, are to blame; therefore I hope His Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties Privy Council will confider of this matter, and adviſe and deſire His Majeſty to take the Advice and Opinion of His Judges, who are His proper Councel therein: For in my poor judgment, and as I have heard from moſt Judicious men, the reſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring this kind of proceeding afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mention'd for Relief againſt unjuſt Decrees in <hi>Chancery,</hi> and other Courts of Equity, will be as much for the Kings Honour and His Subjects Good, as any other part of his Juriſdiction: For I ſay again, there is no Rob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bery, Piracy, Burglary, or other Villany whatſoever, ſo miſchievous
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:62733:73"/>and inſupportable, as the unjuſt ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king away of a mans Eſtate by colour of doing Juſtice, and therefore moſt worthy of His Majeſties care to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent. <hi>Cum Index indulgeat indigno nonne ad prolaptionis contagium pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocat univerſos,</hi> Bract, 107.</p>
               <p>I expect to be Cenſur'd by ſome for what is here ſet down, though I challenge all mankind to charge me with any miſrecital or falſe quotation; but that which moſt troubles me, is my conſciouſneſs of my own unabili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to perform the matter, leaſt a good Cauſe ſhould ſuffer by ill ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nagement: However, having done my beſt, I hope it will be taken in good part by all Honeſt men; more I cannot do, leſs I durſt not for my Oaths ſake; and if any be offended with me, this ſhall be my Sanctuary,</p>
               <q>
                  <hi>Fiat Juſticia ſi ruat Coelum.</hi>
               </q>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
